<stringtable version="120">
  <language name="English">
    <string _locid="120000">The Lakota Nation is made up of three geographically different divisions of peoples who speak varying dialects of the Siouan language: the Lakota, Dakota, and Nakota. In the language of Lakota, the names Lakota, Dakota, and Nakota mean “friends.” The Lakota lived on the Great Plains of the western United States and survived primarily by hunting. Their favorite game was the American bison, or buffalo, which provided food, clothing, and shelter.\n \nThey were excellent horsemen, famed for their ability to fire bows and guns accurately while riding at full gallop. Experts at horse breeding, they owned horses both fast and clever. These animals were considered extremely valuable, and some warriors owned hundreds of them. They were used not only for war, but also as a medium of exchange.\n \nOne of history’s most renowned Lakota warriors was Sitting Bull, known also as Tatanka Yotanka (1831-1890). Born in the territory now known as South Dakota, he was revered as a Lakota principal chief, healer, and prophet. Sitting Bull led Native resistance against U.S. government attempts to take over tribal lands, which included his involvement in the Battle of the Little Bighorn (or the Battle of the Greasy Grass as the victorious Lakota named it). After spending several years in Canada with his followers, Sitting Bull returned to the U.S. under a government amnesty program. Sitting Bull's leading war chiefs were Crazy Horse and Gall.</string>
    <string _locid="120001">The U.S. Army considered the Apache as one of their most difficult opponents during the entire period known as the Indian Wars. Even though their numbers were relatively small, the Apache proved an extremely tough and difficult foe.\n \nThe tribal people known by the name “Apache” inhabited the American Southwest, from at least the sixteenth century until today. The word "Apache" is probably derived from the Zuni word “apachu” meaning enemy. The historic Apache were primarily a nomadic people who lived as hunters-gatherers. They kept few possessions and didn’t settle in one location for long. Apache life centered around a matriarchal culture, with the family its core unit.\n \nThe Apache nation consisted of several loosely knit tribes, including the Mescaleros, Chiricahua, and Coyoteros. The warriors of these groups were famed for their bravery and cunning. During the early 1800s, the Apache fought a series of skirmishes with Mexico along the southern U.S. border. They even sided with the Texans during their fight with Mexico, and maintained good relations with the Texans for some years after Texan independence. Unfortunately for them, the Apaches couldn’t stop the inexorable westward advance of the U.S. in the 1900s, and after a series of hard-fought battles, were driven to reservations.\n \nThe Apache deeply loved the lands of the Southwest and lamented their confinement to reservations. Geronimo, the most famous of all Apache, wrote of his love for the lands of his youth in his biography. “There is no climate or soil which, to my mind, is equal to that of Arizona... It is my land, my home, my fathers' land, to which I now ask to be allowed to return.”</string>
    <string _locid="120002">The name Cheyenne is linked to the Dakota Lakota term for the tribe, Sahiyenan, thought to mean "people of different speech." The Cheyenne call themselves Tsitsistas, which translates to - as is the case with many Native American tribal names - “the people.”\n \nOriginally an agricultural people, the Cheyenne took up the buffalo hunting lifestyle similar to that of the Lakota as the U.S. westward expansion forced them onto the Great Plains. They were excellent horsemen, and (unlike those of most other tribes) their buffalo hunts involved both men and women. Along with the meat provided (including the much prized heart, brain, liver, and kidneys), the buffalo’s hide was used to make winter clothing, teepee coverings, and blankets.\n \nThe Cheyenne were made up of many different clans, spread across a large geographic area. Their size offered both a blessing and a curse. Because they were so widespread, the Cheyenne have managed to keep their identity intact to this day. Unfortunately, however, individual Cheyenne clans often suffered unjust retribution at the hands of the U.S. military for supposed offenses they may or may not have committed. The Sand Creek Massacre in 1864 epitomized this cycle of violence; over 150 innocent Cheyenne and Arapaho were slaughtered in an unwarranted attack that shocked many even during that period of great conflict.</string>
    <string _locid="120003">The name “Huron” is derived from the French word “hure,” meaning ruffian. A derogatory term, it was applied to the Huron. They once lived in territory that became southern Ontario. Over time, the various Huron clans dispersed across the upper Midwest, settling in Ohio, Michigan, and Wisconsin.\n \nThe Huron (also known as Wyandot) were an agricultural people who lived in small communities of as many as 1,000 tribal members. In their often heavily fortified villages, they constructed communal longhouses up to 200 feet long. Like the Haudenosaunee, who spoke a related language, the Huron depended on the staple crops of corn, beans, and squash, with hunting and fishing providing additional food.\n \nAlso like the Haudenosaunee, the Huron established a confederation of separate tribal nations, in their case, four. Established around the middle of the fifteenth century, the confederation ended wars of blood feuds between rival clans by laying out common guidelines for trade and the resolution of disputes. Membership in this confederation was strictly voluntary.\n \nExperts at constructing birch-bark canoes, the Huron established a trade network that stretched beyond their homelands. The early French traders/explorers (voyageurs) established a relationship with the Huron that lasted for years, long after France’s influence on what became U.S. territory waned.</string>
    <string _locid="120004">Located in modern-day south-central Oregon, the Klamath people were quite successful at living off the myriad of resources provided by the rivers, lakes, and lands of their territory. Extremely resourceful, the Klamath had a diet including over forty different species of mammals and fowl. They hunted with bow and arrow, nets, and nooses, and feasted upon an abundance of plants, seeds, and shellfish.\n \nThe Klamath lived in relative seclusion for thousands of years until 1826, when Peter Skeen Ogden - a fur trapper for the Hudson’s Bay Company - arrived in Oregon. More white settlers soon followed. After a few skirmishes, the treaty of 1864 moved the Klamath to a reservation. Inevitably, the culture of the Klamath changed, but their resourcefulness and ingenuity helped them to prosper for decades - in fact, during the 1950s they were one of the richest tribes in the entire U.S.\n \nThe Klamath were a very spiritual people. Crater Lake (known to the Klamath as “giwas”) held a special place in their spiritual lives and was a common destination for spirit quests. The lake was considered a dangerous realm, with spirits supposedly lurking in the depth and humans and mysterious animals inhabiting the lake floor.</string>
    <string _locid="120005">The Mapuche lived in the modern-day countries of Argentina and Chile and were among that region's first settlers. Hunting, gathering, and small farm plots where they cultivated crops such as potatoes provided most of their food. The Mapuche typically lived in small, widespread communities oriented around family units. Their homes, known as rukas, were wooden huts with thatched roofs. In times of war, the Mapuche would band together for protection in larger groups and choose a “toqui” as leader.\n \nThe relative stability the Mapuche lived in for centuries was shattered by the encroach of the Spanish during the sixteenth century. The Spanish believed they could easily conquer the Mapuche and their lands. They were mistaken.\n \nThe Mapuche were fierce warriors, skilled with the hand axe, and consistently battled back the Spanish. After more than a century of warfare, the Spanish admitted defeat and signed a treaty granting the Mapuche rights to their own lands.</string>
    <string _locid="120006">Native to the desert Southwest, the Navajo nation remains one of the largest Native American tribes in existence. Calling themselves “Dine,” which means “the people,” the Navajo share a common ancestral heritage with their neighbors, the Apache.\n \nThe Navajo traditionally dwelt in homes called hogans, constructed of logs, tree bark, and mud. Within Navajo religion, the hogan is a sacred place, used for ceremonies as well as daily living. The Navajo are a very creative and artistic people, evidenced by their skills in silversmithing and pottery. They are noted for their sense of humor and love of laughter - in fact, the first time a Navajo child laughs out loud is cause for family celebration.\n \nIn the 1600s, the Navajo began to use the horses brought to the continent by the Spanish. The horse quickly became a key part of their economy and military strategy. The first recorded instance where Native Americans used horses was in 1659, when the Spanish Governor of the New Mexico colony noted an attack by Navajo warriors on horseback.\n \nDuring War World II, the U.S. Marine Corps used the Navajo language as a secret code to baffle enemy forces in the South Pacific. The Navajo tongue is extremely complex and was learned by few outside the tribe. The code was never cracked and proved extremely valuable, particularly during the battle of Iwo Jima.</string>
    <string _locid="120007">The Zapotec, a Mesoamerican people who developed an advanced civilization, inhabited cities as well as towns, their homes built from stones and mortar. They had an early written language system, which perhaps influenced other Mesoamerican writing systems developed by the Aztec, Maya, and Mixtec.\n \nThe Zapotec lived in the Oaxaca region of modern Mexico, with a marvelous capital city of Monte Alban. They were advanced both socially and militarily - indeed, they managed to maintain their autonomy from the larger Aztec empire. They held out from the Spanish invaders until the mid sixteenth century.\n \nThe name “Zapotec” was given them by their rivals to the north, the Aztec. However, their creation tales spoke of their origins from supernatural beings from above, hence their native name Ben 'Zaa, or “people of the clouds.”</string>
    <string _locid="120008">Cuauhtemoc was Moctezuma’s nephew and son-in-law, and is known as the final emperor of the Aztec. His name can be translated as “descending eagle.” Born in about 1500, Cuauhtemoc became emperor around the age of twenty-five after the deaths of Moctezuma and his successor, Cuitlahuac. At the time of his ascension to power, Cuauhtemoc was already well known as a great warrior and leader.\n \nHis reign lasted but a few months. After being driven from the Aztec capital of Tenochtitlan, the Spanish under Cortez regrouped in the city of Tlaxcala, bolstering their forces with indigenous warriors who had long awaited their chance to strike back at the Aztec. The final siege of Tenochtitlan - where Aztec resolve struggled against Spanish gunpowder and steel - lasted barely three months. Cuauhtemoc was forced to surrender to Cortez and the Aztec empire was finished.\n \nBut the story of Cuauhtemoc doesn’t end with disgrace. Cortez’s royal treasurer, Aldrete, had Cuauhtemoc tortured with fire in an effort to get him to reveal the Aztec secret storerooms of gold. But even with his feet in the flames, Cuauhtemoc steadfastly maintained none existed. Realizing the fruitlessness of this, Cortez took Cuauhtemoc into his own custody afterwards, but had him executed during an expedition into modern-day Honduras in 1525. Today Cuauhtemoc is revered throughout modern Mexico as a brave and honorable warrior who maintained his integrity to the very end.\n \nIn Age of Empires III: Definitive Edition, Cuauhtemoc is a fierce warrior willing to take practically any measure to ensure victory. He’s confident, proud, and able to make good on any threat.</string>
    <string _locid="120009">As with any great historic figure, it is sometimes hard to distinguish between legend and reality. The character described in Longfellow’s famous poem, “The Song of Hiawatha” scarcely resembles one of history’s most beloved Native American heroes.\n \nPrecise historic details about Hiawatha are hard to uncover. We know that he was a Mohawk of Onondaga and a disciple of the Huron prophet Deganawidah, who was known as “The Great Peacemaker.” Hiawatha also was famed for his abilities as a skilled peacemaker, as well as a powerful orator.\n \nTogether, Hiawatha and Deganawidah are remembered as the founders of the great Haudenosaunee Confederacy in the sixteenth century, which brought together the Mohawk, Oneida, Onondaga, Cayuga, and Seneca, and later the Tuscarora. The longhouse was chosen to symbolize the new confederation and the importance of different peoples working for a common purpose.\n \nIn Age of Empires III: Definitive Edition, Hiawatha leads his warriors courageously and without pause. He doesn’t linger over decisions, nor does he waste words on trivialities. He has a vision for his people and will not let any one or any nation stand in his way.</string>
    <string _locid="120010">Chief Gall was born in 1840 and grew up on the plains of South Dakota. His name was given to him when, as a hungry orphan, he ate the gall bladder of an animal. Before this event, his name was “Bear shedding his hair.” He fought with Chief Red Cloud at Big Mound and other battles around the years 1866 to 1868.\n \nA renowned warrior and leader, he was one of Sitting Bull’s war chiefs during the Lakota assault on General Custer during the Battle of the Greasy Grass (also known as the Battle of the Little Bighorn). It was a great victory, but both Gall and Sitting Bull realized that the U.S. government would return with many more soldiers bent on revenge. Therefore, to protect their people, Gall, Sitting Bull, and other Lakota fled with their families to Canada.\n \nEventually, Gall and Sitting Bull parted ways and Gall returned to the U.S. to settle down on the Standing Rock Indian Reservation. Gall became a prominent supporter of assimilation into European culture, even serving in 1889 as a judge on Standing Rock’s Court of Indian Offenses. He died in South Dakota on 5 December 1894; the following words were inscribed on his memorial: “An Honest Man Should Always Be Remembered.”\n \nIn Age of Empires III: Definitive Edition, Gall has seen the sun set on many battlefields. He is wise to the ways of his enemies and the spirit world upon which he relies. But don’t mistake his calm demeanor for weakness: Gall and his Lakota warriors can strike with deadly speed.</string>
    <string _locid="120011">The precursor to modern machine guns, the Gatling Gun is a rapid-fire artillery unit that can chew up opponents at a brisk pace. It has good range and hitpoints, and offers a powerful attack.\n \nThis unit is available only after a player has Revolted.</string>
    <string _locid="120012">The Gatling gun was invented by Richard Gatling in 1861. Although not precisely a machine gun, it nonetheless offered devastating firepower for its time. The operator of the gun would turn a hand crank, which rotated six gun barrels around a central shaft. Cartridges were continuously fed into the barrels as they made their rotation.\n \nThe Gatling gun saw its first limited action on the battlefields of the U.S. Civil War, where its rapid fire of up to 600 rounds a minute proved extremely deadly. The gun was also used in multiple conflicts worldwide during the latter half of the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, until it eventually was replaced by the modern machine gun, with its automatic action.</string>
    <string _locid="120013">This horse-drawn artillery unit offers good speed and mobility at a relatively low cost. The Horse Artillery unit enables you to position cannon easily and quickly during a battle.</string>
    <string _locid="120014">Sometime around the sixteenth century, military planners began to see the value of using horses to maneuver light artillery to the front lines of battle. European records show that some commanders integrated their horse artillery units with infantry units and even cavalry. The mobility of horse artillery units offered military leaders increased options in dealing with fluid and rapidly changing battlefield conditions.</string>
    <string _locid="120015">The Light Cannon is a land-based siege unit with a long range. Its attacks can do peripheral damage to units and objects near its target. It's good against artillery, infantry units, and buildings. It is available from the Siege Workshop in the fourth Age or from the Tribal Council.</string>
    <string _locid="120016">Most Haudenosaunee campaigns ended up with siege warfare. This fact, combined with the Haudenosaunee predilection for modern weapons (trade steel and gunpowder), meant that they learned to deal with military technology early in their history. The cannon was a natural step in this development. The Light Cannon represents an artillery piece, bought or stolen from European allies, but crewed by Haudenosaunee warriors.</string>
    <string _locid="120017">The Mantlet is an infantry unit with a strong attack, plenty of hitpoints, good range, and decent resistance to damage. Because a Mantlet can withstand enemy fire, it's good at attacking towers and other buildings. It does damage at range. Therefore, it's wise to maintain this range whenever possible. Mantlets can be upgraded to Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120018">The Petard is a small explosive device, primarily used at close range to break down walls and other defensive structures. They're relatively inexpensive, and you'll find them very useful in siege attacks.</string>
    <string _locid="120019">The term petard first emerged during medieval times, referring to a small and notoriously unstable explosive device similar in concept and usage to the modern grenade. The name probably derives from the Latin "petar," which means, "to break wind" (an example of the military mind's wry sense of humor.)\n \nTo be "hoisted by one's own petard" is a phrase commonly thought to mean something along the lines of "being hung with your own rope"; or, to stay true to the actual context of an explosive device, to be blown up by your own bomb. The saying is derived from Shakespeare's Hamlet. The bard wrote:\n \n"For 'tis the sport to have the engineer\nHoist with his own petar"</string>
    <string _locid="120020">The Ram is a land-based siege unit with short range and a high-building attack. Slow and lumbering, it's quite effective at reducing an enemy town to rubble.</string>
    <string _locid="120021">The most direct way to attack a stone wall or other stone fortification was to knock it down with a battering ram. A typical ram was a stout log mounted on wheels or suspended from a frame so it could swing forward and backward. The frame was brought up to the wall or gate to be battered; men heaving in unison then repeatedly slammed the ram into the target. Given enough time, any obstruction could be knocked down, opening a breach for assault.</string>
    <string _locid="120022">The Axe Rider cavalry unit is good against artillery; it has a big attack, good speed, and no range. Because the Axe Rider does damage in melee combat, it is vulnerable to ranged attacks when moving in close, though closing is not a common strategy of cavalry units. You can upgrade the Axe Rider to Elite and Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120023">When the Lakota discovered horses, they were so impressed they named the new animal the Wonder Dog. It changed their entire way of life. Almost overnight, they became one of the most famous nomad peoples of history. Their effectiveness in combat is best summed up by the fact that the Lakota were long considered the best cavalry in the world.</string>
    <string _locid="120024">The Bow Rider is a cavalry unit with a dangerous ranged attack, good hitpoints, and excellent speed. He can move in and out of combat quickly. Because he's armed with a bow, however, he isn't very effective in melee combat.</string>
    <string _locid="120025">When forced west by the encroachment of the European colonists, the Lakota adapted to a wide-ranging, nomadic lifestyle - aided primarily by their mastery of the horse. The Lakota were known as expert horsemen and horse breeders. They developed extremely sophisticated riding tactics. When in battle, they would wrap their legs about their horse's upper body and lean over to the side opposite their foes - taking aim from beneath the horse's neck and using the animal for cover.</string>
    <string _locid="120026">The Comanchero is a mercenary infantry unit available only from the Saloon. He has a good ranged attack, but not many hitpoints. Keep him out of range of enemy attacks whenever possible, and use him from a distance. </string>
    <string _locid="120027">The name “comanchero” refers to those non-Indians, especially the Spanish, who traded with the Comanches of New Mexico. During the late 1800s in the U.S. Southwest, comancheros inhabited a shadowy world of commerce between dealers of guns, ammunition, and other forbidden commodities with the local Native Americans. Even though the Lakota, Apache, and other Native Americans were quite often provided firearms by the U.S. military, a significant black market emerged that the comancheros were more than happy to exploit. </string>
    <string _locid="120028">The Tokala Soldier is a cavalry unit armed with a spear that is good against light infantry and artillery. Tokala Soldiers can only be obtained from Community Plaza ceremonies or from the Tribal Council.</string>
    <string _locid="120029">The Kanya Horseman is a cavalry unit with a big attack, good speed, and no range. Armed with clubs and axes, the Kanya Horseman does its damage in melee combat. It is vulnerable to ranged attacks as it moves in close (though, as a cavalry unit, it takes less time to close). It can be upgraded to Elite and Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120030">The Haudenosaunee were a woodland people, so did not live in good horse country. Naturally, they adopted horses from the European colonists, but the Six Nations’ warriors were usually more comfortable fighting on foot. Despite this, the advantage of horses for scouting and quick raids was so obvious that the Haudenosaunee did use them in warfare when they were needed.</string>
    <string _locid="120031">Musket Riders are a fast, ranged unit. They are effective at raiding and chasing down enemy cavalry. Their range is short, and they can be vulnerable to longer-ranged warriors. They can be upgraded to Champion.\n \nMusket Riders have a good measure of everything that makes a unit effective: speed, some range, and hitpoints. They do cost more population space than infantry, but infantry can't catch them.</string>
    <string _locid="120032">The Haudenosaunee fondness for guns and willingness to adopt new modes of warfare meant that they quickly applied the use of firearms to mounted warriors. Unlike the old European tradition, among the Haudenosaunee the mounted warriors were not necessarily considered the highest-ranking or noblest.</string>
    <string _locid="120033">The Rifle Rider cavalry unit has good speed, hitpoints, and, unlike other ranged cavalry units, an effective ranged attack against heavy infantry. You can upgrade the Rifle Rider to Elite and Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120034">The ultimate development of the famous Lakota art of war were their amazingly skilled horsemen armed with repeating rifles. There is an old stereotype that the American Indians were reactionary culturally, unable to adapt to modern ways. The Lakota rifle riders demonstrate the falseness of this idea – during their heyday, they were the most advanced warriors on Earth. In Europe at this time, cavalry were still fighting with sabers and lances. Even in America, the U.S. cavalry used single-shot rifles, significantly inferior to the Lakota carbines.</string>
    <string _locid="120035">The Tashunke Prowler is a special cavalry unit with Stealth ability, a big attack, good speed, and no range. First available in the second Age, the Tashunke Prowler gains strength through numbers - the more you have, the tougher they get. A melee fighter, this unit is primarily armed with coup sticks.</string>
    <string _locid="120036">The primary means for a Plains warrior to gain glory on the battlefield involved acts of courage in battle - such as killing enemies, stealing horses, or taking weapons - which won prestige and enabled an individual to rise above fellow tribesmen as a warrior and leader.\n \nFor some groups, the highest honor of all was given to those warriors who managed to get close enough to touch an enemy and escape without killing him - a practice known as counting coup ("coup" is a French word meaning "blow"). A warrior could make contact with his hand, a weapon such as a club, spear, or bow, or even a specially crafted coup stick.</string>
    <string _locid="120037">The Aenna is a ranged infantry unit that's cheap to produce and available early. You can upgrade it to Elite and Champion.\n \nAenna units are best fielded against slow, non-ranged units, so that they have time to fire a deadly barrage of arrows before they are forced to flee or fight hand to hand.</string>
    <string _locid="120038">Before the coming of the Europeans, the main missile weapon of the Haudenosaunee was the bow. Even after muskets became available, bows were still widely used for hunting and warfare, because bows were inexpensive and did not depend on unreliable trade ties for gunpowder.</string>
    <string _locid="120039">The Aztec Arrow Knight is a relatively slow infantry unit with a big attack, a lot of hitpoints, and a medium range. The Arrow Knight fires flaming arrows at long range and is particularly effective against buildings and artillery. You can upgrade this unit to Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120040">The Aztec Empire incorporated many neighboring Mesoamerican cultures in a complex mix of trade and tribute. Warriors from neighboring tribes were often called to duty by the Aztec as they expanded throughout the region.\n \nThe arrow knights, not Aztec by birth, were allies or subject peoples called into service. Their primary weapon was the atlatl, a leverage device that enabled its user to accurately hurl a spear up to 150 yards.</string>
    <string _locid="120041">Cetan Bows are an inexpensive, ranged light infantry unit. Inexpensive to produce and available early, their range starts out very poor, but increases dramatically with their first upgrade. Available upgrades include Elite and Champion.\n \nCetan Bows are best fielded against slow, non-ranged units so that they have time to fire a deadly barrage of arrows before they are forced to flee or fight hand to hand.</string>
    <string _locid="120042">Before the Lakota adoption of horses, they waged war and hunted on foot, armed with bows powerful enough to penetrate a buffalo’s tough hide. They used both simple and compound bows, made of wood and elk sinew. Their arrowheads were sometimes stone, but often iron. The Lakota bartered extensively with American and Canadian traders for iron points. Some surviving Lakota arrows are actually tipped with iron nails – the Lakota were a practical folk. If it worked, they used it. </string>
    <string _locid="120043">The Revolutionary is a ranged infantry unit comparable to a Musketeer and only available in revolutions. Once you have revolted, all your settlers drop their work and pick up guns to turn into Revolutionaries and take the battle to the enemy base. Instead of villagers, your Town Center now produces Revolutionaries. Like Musketeers they counter cavalry with their bayonets in melee combat. Unlike most gunpowder infantry units, Revolutionaries are also countering cavalry with their ranged attack. Some revolutions have more powerful Revolutionaries, special upgrade shipments, or unique replacements. Revolutionaries only cost food, which makes it easier to replenish the ranks in a revolution when the economy largely relies on Trading Posts and Factories.</string>
    <string _locid="120044">The European empires in the New World lasted in most cases for a little more than 300 years. By the early nineteenth century most European colonies had thrown off their Old World masters and had become independent nations through revolutionary wars. The first revolution by the Thirteen British colonies resulted in the eventual formation of the United States. The success of this revolution was assured when the United States stated its Monroe Doctrine, forbidding any power from further conquests or colony placement in the Americas, and Great Britain made it clear that its navy would not allow such actions either.\n\nSoon other occupied countries in the Americas and Europe were to follow the example of the successful revolution in North America. The French Revolution of 1789 toppled the Bourbon monarchy that had ruled France for 200 years. The Greeks and Serbians put an end to Ottoman rule. Revolutionary armies in the Americas were often led by experienced officers and generals who prior to the revolution served in the military of the colonial powers, and not seldomly were of European heritage. The military skills of revolutionary leaders like Simón Bolívar, José de San Martín, or Bernardo O'Higgins were of paramount importance in liberating Latin America from centuries of Spanish and Portuguese colonial rule. Not all wars of liberation were immediately successful. The revolutions and rebellions in Ireland, Poland, Romania, and Hungary took several attempts before eventually succeeding.</string>
    <string _locid="120045">The Coyote Runner is an agile, fast, armored warrior able to perform some of a true cavalry unit's duties at lower cost. This unit is good against skirmishers and artillery.\n \nBecause the Coyote Runner does damage in melee combat, it's vulnerable to ranged attacks as it closes in. In the later Ages, you can upgrade the Coyote Runner to Elite and Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120046">Humorous, playful, and unpredictable, the coyote was considered sacred to the Aztec as well as many other Native peoples, and the Aztec coyote runner strove to emulate the animal's qualities in battle. Coyote runners wore teeth and fur to symbolize the coyote's physical appearance, coupled with bright colors and feathers to illustrate its capricious nature.\n \nThe coyote runners were all left-handed because that made them more dangerous in combat.</string>
    <string _locid="120047">The Eagle Runner Knight is an Aztec infantry unit with a good attack and decent range. The Eagle Runner Knight flings spears from an atlatl, and is good against cavalry and hand shock infantry.</string>
    <string _locid="120048">Aztec warriors who had captured at least four enemy soldiers became eligible for the ranks of the eagle runner knight or the jaguar prowl knights. Presumably, this emphasis on capturing enemies was to collect a pool of captives for sacrifice, but the Aztec were also known for dealing death in battle, killing with single strokes of their obsidian swords, or hurling barbed spears with atlatls. Their own warriors who caused confusion or disorder in ranks were beaten on the spot and sometimes killed.\n \nThe dress of eagle runner knights incorporated feathers and a helmet resembling an eagle's head. The eagle was a symbol of the sun, the focus of Aztec worship and sacrifice. Eagle runner knights are usually depicted carrying shields and spears.</string>
    <string _locid="120049">The Forest Prowler is a light infantry unit armed with a rifle. The unit has a long range and Stealth ability. It's good against slow, heavy infantry, while it's at a disadvantage in hand-to-hand fighting. You can upgrade it to Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120050">The classic stereotype of the Haudenosaunee, even today, is the stealthy warrior slinking cat-like through the woods, senses keen, and armed with a loaded musket. Haudenosaunee ambushes could be devastating, as unseen enemies opened fire on European troop columns from bushes and trees. The usual response for a defeated enemy was to retreat to a town or fort, which is when of course the Haudenosaunee would unleash their feared siege techniques.\n \nThe Haudenosaunee preferred this kind of shadowy warfare. Its effectiveness was proven by the fact that the Americans adopted these techniques in their revolution against the British in 1776. The Americans had been taught how to use the forests by the Haudenosaunee themselves, in their periodic conflicts. </string>
    <string _locid="120051">The Jaguar Prowl Knight is an unique Aztec melee infantry available armed with a razor-sharp obsidian blade. It is available at the Nobles’ Hut starting in the Fortress Age and classified as a Heavy infantry unit with bonus damage against cavalry and other heavy infantry. As such it has decent speed, attack and hitpoints. These warriors are skilled veterans and have learnt the Stealth ability that prevents enemy soldiers to see them coming - like a prowling jaguar.</string>
    <string _locid="120249">The Jaguar Prowl Knight is an unique Aztec melee infantry available armed with a razor-sharp obsidian blade. It is available at the Nobles’ Hut starting in the Fortress Age and classified as a Shock infantry unit, assuming the role of Heavy hand cavalry for the Aztecs. As such it has decent speed, attack and hitpoints. These warriors are skilled veterans and have learnt the Stealth ability that prevents enemy soldiers to see them coming - like a prowling jaguar.</string>
    <string _locid="120052">Aztec warriors who had captured at least four enemy soldiers became eligible for the ranks of the eagle runner knights or the jaguar prowl knights. Presumably this emphasis on capturing enemies was to collect a pool of captives for sacrifice, but the Aztecs were well-known for dealing death in battle, killing with single strokes of their obsidian swords or hurling atlatl-driven flights of barbed spears. Warriors who caused confusion or disorder in the ranks were beaten on the spot and sometimes killed.\n \nThe dress of jaguar prowl knights incorporated bright colors and spots to evoke the imagery of a jaguar. The jaguar was a symbol of the night, a prowler and a predator, an appropriate model for an elite warrior. Jaguar prowl knights are usually depicted carrying shields and obsidian swords.</string>
    <string _locid="120053">The Aztec Otontin Slinger is an infantry unit with a good attack and decent range. The Otontin Slinger is best used for ranged attacks and is most effective against heavy infantry such as Musketeers and Pikemen.\n \nWearing simple cotton armor and armed with slings and shields, the Otontin Slinger is the Aztec's cheapest and weakest unit. Available upgrades are Elite and Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120054">In Aztec society, membership in the calpulli established each individual's religious and secular schooling, as well as how they would be trained in warfare. The men of a calpulli served together in battle and on the numerous public works projects. Their soldiers wielded weapons of wood and stone, and they often sought prisoners to be sacrificed in religious ceremonies.\n \nThe macehualtin, who comprised the majority of the Aztec population, labored as farmers, tradesmen, and merchants. During times of war and conquest, they took up arms as needed. </string>
    <string _locid="120055">The Pistolero is a ranged mercenary infantry unit available only from the Saloon. He has a decent ranged attack, and good hitpoints. He is reasonably fast and works best at close range, so make sure to use him as the advance guard for your forces.</string>
    <string _locid="120056">On a dusty street, two steely eyed men grimly face one another. A moment of dread anticipation as a tumbleweed rolls past.. and then, two hands slap leather and pistols bark death. When the smoke passes, only one man still stands.\n \nThe mythos of the American Old West would not be nearly so compelling without its archetypal protagonist: the gunslinger (or pistolero). Their names have become the stuff of legend: Wild Bill Hickok, Billy the Kid, Wyatt Earp and his gun fight at the OK Corral.\n \nBut the reality of a gunfight is never quite as dramatic as depicted. The epic mano-a-mano showdown in the street is more a fixture of Hollywood than history. Most fights resembled drunken brawls, often involving fists and blades rather than bullets. And while some of the most famous gunslingers did meet their makers through showdown or ambush, many others simply passed away after living out their days recounting tall tales of improbable glory. </string>
    <string _locid="120057">The Puma Spearman is a spear-bearing infantry unit with decent hitpoints and damage, but no range. This unit does all of its damage in melee combat. Puma Spearmen are good against cavalry or buildings. You can upgrade the Puma Spearman to Elite and Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120058">In Aztec society, membership in the calpulli established each individual's religious and secular schooling, as well as how they would be trained in warfare. The men of a calpulli served together in battle and on the numerous public works projects. Their soldiers wielded weapons of wood and stone, and they often sought prisoners to be sacrificed in religious ceremonies.\n \nTo the Aztecs, the puma was a respected predator and held religious significance within their pantheon of gods. The Spanish recorded that Montezuma kept a puma-like creature called the cuitlamiztli (or wolf-cat) in his private zoo. Mexican legends refer to the existence of the onza, a long-legged and extremely aggressive cat native to the region.</string>
    <string _locid="120059">The Renegado is a mercenary infantry unit available only from the Saloon. He has a good ranged attack, but not many hitpoints. Keep them out of range of enemy attacks whenever possible, and use them from a distance.</string>
    <string _locid="120060">The broad expanses of the North American Old West offered many different opportunities to make one's fortune – either within the boundaries of the law, or by simply preying on others who had already done so. Anyone known as a rengado - Spanish for “renegade” - was almost certainly a gruff and surly individual who had little use for society’s traditions or laws. Mark Twain’s “A Horse’s Tale” mentions one such character, “Trap-robber, horse-thief, squaw-man, renegado - Hank Butters - I know him very well.”</string>
    <string _locid="120061">The Skull Knight is a slow-moving, elite infantry unit with a lot of hitpoints and no range. A powerful melee fighter, the Skull Knight is vulnerable to ranged attacks.</string>
    <string _locid="120062">In Aztec society, membership in the calpulli established each individual's religious and secular schooling, as well as how they would be trained in warfare. The men of a calpulli served together in battle and on the numerous public works projects. Their soldiers wielded weapons of wood and stone, and they often sought prisoners to be sacrificed in religious ceremonies.\n \nThe most-feared and powerful division in the Aztec army was made up of skull knights. Their name, Tzitzimitl, translates as "frightful specters," the skull knight dressed as a kind of undead horror, and the enemy often fled at their advance.</string>
    <string _locid="120063">The Tomahawk is an Haudenosaunee infantry unit that's good against cavalry, with a good attack and short range. The Tomahawk does its damage at range - and it is good to maintain this range whenever possible.</string>
    <string _locid="120064">The Wakina Rifle is an infantry unit with excellent range and damage, but relatively few hitpoints and a poor melee attack. They cannot stand long against tougher infantry or the cavalry units that close in on them.\n \nWakina Rifles tend to do well against non-ranged infantry because they can cause a lot of damage while the enemy infantry close. They are effective against other infantry, but cavalry will mow down Wakina Rifles if they can get close.</string>
    <string _locid="120065">Sometimes the Lakota had to fight on foot. It is not always possible to run someone down with your horse. On these occasions, they fought tenaciously and well. In general, the Lakota were known for their keen accuracy with their rifles.</string>
    <string _locid="120066">The Club Warrior is an inexpensive Lakota hand infantry unit with decent hitpoints and damage, but no range. This infantry unit does all its damage in melee combat.\n \nClub Warriors are best fielded against cavalry or buildings. They are inexpensive to train, cost no Coin, and may be trained in the Commerce Age. You can upgrade Club Warriors to Elite and Champion.</string>
    <string _locid="120067">The Lakota constructed their war clubs out of a variety of substances: stone, wood, bone, antlers, horn, and sometimes incorporated steel blades. The one consistent feature was an efficacy in combat. One blow from one of these deadly weapons could cripple or kill a grizzly bear, let alone a human opponent.</string>
    <string _locid="120068">The Warrior comes, when needed, from the Call the People Ceremony at the Community Plaza. He is an infantry unit with a good attack and short range. The Warrior does his damage at range; maintain this range whenever possible. These Warriors are good emergency defense, but they are not good additions to a fighting army.</string>
    <string _locid="120069">Long before recorded history, humans have sought ways to connect with nature and one another. The tradition of Native Americans express that core desire in many different ways. More than recreation, the ceremony was a way to share the concerns, dreams, and fears of the tribal unit. Tribal members danced to chants and drums, flutes, and other musical instruments.\n \nCeremonies had a variety of purposes: for a plentiful harvest, such as the Corn Grinding Song of the Zuni; as a prayer for rain during the scorching time of summer, such as the Hopi Snake Ceremony; and to bring forth better hunting, such as the Deer Ceremony of the Navajo. No matter the tribe or season, the ceremony itself is better understood as a means of prayer and communion with the great and mysterious powers of the spirit world. </string>
    <string _locid="120070">Mercenaries are usually very strong versions of their base unit type, whether melee or ranged, infantry or cavalry. They can be sent from the Home City, Holy Sites, or Tribal Council after they are unlocked. They are the only Home City Shipments that cost Coin.\n\nAsian civilizations can train repentant mercenaries from the Monastery, while European civilizations can train mercenaries from the Saloon. Different units are available on different maps. Look for Ninjas on the Great Plains or Mamelukes in Araucania. Mercenaries are a good choice to send or train if you have the Coin to spare, especially if your enemy is using them.</string>
    <string _locid="120071">The Elmeti were non-noble knights of Italy. Their name is derived form the Italian term for helmet, referring to the headgear they wore along with their finely crafted plate armor. The Elmeti fought in a series of skirmishes between Italy and other European states during the latter half of the fifteenth century. One key battle occurred in 1487 at Ponte di Crevola, where the Milanese army, led by Trivulzio, defeated Swiss forces in a battle that foreshadowed nearly a half century of further European encroaches into Italy - a period now known as the Italian Wars.</string>
    <string _locid="120072">The first flintlocks appeared in the early 1600s, and quickly spread across Europe. The flintlock applied mechanical principles to strike flint to steel, using the resulting spark to ignite black powder and send a bullet (or ball) on its way. Extremely reliable under almost all conditions (including rainy weather), the flintlock musket remained the primary weapon for infantry for nearly 200 years, up to and including the U.S. Civil War.</string>
    <string _locid="120073">Artillery has existed for hundreds of years, practically since the invention of gunpowder. Early artillery, such as the great bombard, was extremely large, heavy, and difficult to maneuver across the field of battle. Military tacticians envisioned the value of more lightweight pieces, leading to the creation of the first mortars in the mid-seventeenth century. Armies soon discovered that the tradeoff in firepower for increased mobility was valuable in certain situations. Today, the mortar and similar weapons play a strong role in the blend of weaponry used in modern combat scenarios.</string>
    <string _locid="120074">Shrouded by the mists of time, the exploits of the ninja continue to fire imaginations across the globe. During the turbulent years of Japan's sixth and seventh centuries, a secret class of warrior priests emerged. Rulers of opposing factions came to value the ninja for their skills in stealth, combat, and espionage.\n \nAs the centuries passed, the legendary powers of the ninja grew: invisibility, shape-shifting, flight; even the ability to pass through solid walls. Modern filmmakers blend historical fact with ancient myth to fashion a portrait of a warrior class that continues to fascinate and terrify.</string>
    <string _locid="120075">The Apache Cavalry unit has good speed, hitpoints, and an effective ranged attack against cavalry.</string>
    <string _locid="120076">The tribal people known by the name “Apache” inhabited the American Southwest, from at least the sixteenth century until today. “Apache” is probably derived from the Zuni word “apachu” meaning enemy.\n \nThe historic Apache were known as primarily a nomadic people who lived as hunters-gatherers. They kept few possessions and didn’t settle in one location for long. Apache life centered around a matriarchal culture, with the family its core unit.\n \nThe Apache nation consisted of several loosely-knit tribes, including the Mescaleros, Chiricahua, and Coyoteros. The warriors of these groups were famed for their bravery and cunning. The U.S. Army considered the Apache as one of their most difficult opponents during the entire period known as the Indian Wars. Even though their numbers were relatively small, the Apache proved an extremely tough and difficult foe.</string>
    <string _locid="120078">Adorned with buffalo-horn headgear, the Cheyenne Rider is a fast mounted cavalry unit with a strong attack. The Cheyenne Rider has good resistance and good hitpoints, but no range. Like most melee units, they are vulnerable to ranged attacks until they can get close enough to their targets to attack.\n \nCheyenne Riders are very good against infantry, in contrast to most cavalry, who generally should avoid engaging infantry. They will still take damage as they run in close to ranged enemy units, but if those units are infantry there had better be a lot of them.</string>
    <string _locid="120079">To the Native peoples of the North American plains, the horse represented both freedom and power. Horses were prized possessions to the Cheyenne, and were significant spoils of war. When armed with a lance, a mounted Cheyenne warrior presented a fearsome foe.\n \nBefore Cheyenne warriors engaged in battle, their leaders carefully planned their raids in detail. To kill one’s enemy in battle was of course a good thing to the Cheyenne warrior. But of even greater importance was the act of touching a living, unhurt man and leave him unscathed, a practice known as “counting coup.” The bravest warriors were known to go into battle with only a coup stick, a twig or carved piece of wood, sometimes decorated with fur or feathers.</string>
    <string _locid="120080">The Huron, also known as the Wyandot, probably numbered between 30,000 and 45,000 in the early 1500s. Even though they generally had good relations with neighboring tribes, their rivalry with the Haudenosaunee did erupt into sporadic warfare. They lived in well-fortified villages with populations over 1,000 and lived in large, communal longhouses up to 200 feet long.\n \nLike other Native peoples, the Huron needed siege weapons when they battled rival villages. One technique they developed was the mantlet, similar in function to those used in Roman and medieval armies. Two warriors would carry the mantlet (essentially a moveable wooden wall) to protect themselves from enemy arrow or musket fire until they reached their enemy’s town walls, where the mantlet was used as a ladder to scale the walls and breach the town.</string>
    <string _locid="120081">The Klamath Rifleman is an infantry unit with a good attack and good range. This unit does its damage at range, so maintain this range whenever possible.</string>
    <string _locid="120082">The Klamath tribes of northern California and Oregon were among the last of the Native American tribes to fight the American settlers trying to take their lands. Late in the 1800s, they fought a war in very difficult terrain, holding off a much superior force for many months. In this bitter struggle, the natives proved especially effective with their rifles.</string>
    <string _locid="120083">The Mapuche Ironwood Clubman is an infantry unit with a big attack, a lot of hitpoints, and no range. Because this unit does its damage in melee combat, it is vulnerable to ranged attacks.</string>
    <string _locid="120084">The relative stability the Mapuche lived in for centuries was shattered by the encroach of the Spanish during the sixteenth century. The Spanish thought they could easily conquer the Mapuche and their lands. They were mistaken.\n \nThe Mapuche were fierce warriors, and consistently battled back the Spanish. After more than a century of warfare, the Spanish admitted defeat and signed a treaty granting the Mapuche rights to their own lands.\n \nThe Mapuche lived in wooden huts with thatched roofs called rukas. Hunting, gathering, and small farm plots where they cultivated crops such as potatoes provided most of their food. They typically lived in small, widespread communities oriented around family units. After the Spanish invasion, however, the Mapuche began to band together for protection in larger groups.</string>
    <string _locid="120085">The Navajo Rifleman is an infantry unit with a good attack and good range. This unit does its damage at range, so maintain this range whenever possible.</string>
    <string _locid="120086">Native Americans obtained rifles and other firearms in various ways. Some were traded by non-Indians for skins and other goods. Others were provided by U.S. government officials to those living on reservations for the purpose of hunting. And a great number were obtained through raids and scavenging battlefields. Regardless of how Native peoples obtained firearms, Native Americans proved remarkably adaptable in leveraging this new technology to their battlefield tactics.\n \nEven though firearms were quite expensive and often difficult to acquire, by no means were the different tribes always outgunned. In fact, during the Battle of the Little Bighorn (also known as the Battle of the Greasy Grass) it’s believed that the Lakota were equipped with several hundred repeating rifles - offering them a significant firepower advantage over the Springfield single-shot carbines held by Custer’s men.</string>
    <string _locid="120087">The Zapotec Lightning Warrior is an infantry unit with a good attack and decent range. This unit does its damage at range, so maintain this range whenever possible.</string>
    <string _locid="120088">The Zapotec, a Mesoamerican people who developed an advanced civilization, inhabited cities as well as towns, their homes built from stones and mortar. They had an early written language system, which perhaps influenced other Mesoamerican writing systems developed as by the Aztec, Maya, and Mixtec.\n \nOne of the most powerful and sacred forces of nature to the Zapotec was lightning, personified by Cociyo or the Thunder God. Images of the Thunder God often reflected a serpentine nature, perhaps mirroring the undulating movements of lightning as it strikes the earth. Dressed for battle in lightweight yet sturdy cotton armor, the lightning warrior was an elite infantryman feared throughout Mesoamerica during the 1500s.</string>
    <string _locid="120089">You can train Canoes from your Dock. They have a decent attack with a relatively short range, but are cheaper than larger ships.\n \nThey can be used as transports and, though it seems unlikely, they can transport cavalry and even artillery.</string>
    <string _locid="120090">The Ironclad is a powerful ship that combines firepower with superior armor, allowing it to dish out and take on significant damage. It has a lot of hitpoints, good range, and a big attack.\n \nThis unit is available only after a player has Revolted.</string>
    <string _locid="120091">Around the middle of the nineteenth century, warships armored with iron plates emerged as the dominant naval vessel during conflicts across the globe. In the U.S. Civil War, the Monitor class of steam-powered warships was developed.\n \nIn March 1862, the legendary first battle of true Ironclads occurred, pitting the U.S.-built Monitor against the Confederacy's Merrimack. After a four-hour struggle, the battle ended inconclusively with the Merrimack withdrawing to deeper water. Even though neither ship emerged victorious, this day heralded the end of the age of wooden warships.</string>
    <string _locid="120092">The Tlaloc Canoe is a fast ship unique to the Aztecs, with a lot of hitpoints and a high attack. It is very powerful against other ships, but vulnerable to buildings and land-based artillery. The Tlaloc Canoe is available in limited number after reaching the Industrial Age.\n \nTlaloc Canoes can be constructed in the New World or sent from the Tribal Council.</string>
    <string _locid="120093">Canoes were widely used by the Aztecs to transport goods throughout Tenochtitlan's many water causeways and canals. (As the Aztecs had neither horses, oxen, nor the wheel, this mode of transport was critical to their economy.) Warriors also used dugout canoes when traveling to remote parts of their empire.</string>
    <string _locid="120094">The War Canoe can fish, scout shorelines, and transport villagers and warriors. It sinks quickly when attacked by other ships or defensive buildings. Artillery units or even a group of ranged attackers can sink a War Canoe within range of their weapons.\n \nEven though your first War Canoe is often free, don't overlook its potential strategic value. Some players ignore their War Canoes, instead focusing on their land activities. Don't make that mistake - using your War Canoes wisely can be key to a successful game. Controlling the waterways of a map gives you free rein to scout, fish, and transport warriors. Therefore, it's important to balance between managing your land and water activities.</string>
    <string _locid="120095">One of the largest canoes used by Native Americans comes from the Pacific Northwest. The people there would make large dugout canoes by hollowing out the huge trees native to the region. For example, the Haida constructed war canoes from 70 to 100 feet long, which could hold as many as sixty warriors. Neighboring tribes, like the Makah, still use similar canoes to hunt whales and other sea mammals.</string>
    <string _locid="120096">The Aztec War Chief is an infantry unit with a big attack, a lot of hitpoints, and no range. Because the Aztec War Chief does damage in melee combat, he is vulnerable to ranged attacks as he moves in close. The primary bonus for the War Chief is that all units near him earn extra Experience Points for kills.\n \nLike Explorers, the War Chief has a good line of sight and can collect Treasures and build Trading Posts.\n \nIf a War Chief falls in a fight, he collapses and has to generate enough hitpoints to be recovered by allies. A fallen War Chief can also be returned to the Community Plaza by doing the War Ceremony.</string>
    <string _locid="120097">The most densely populated region of the New World in 1492 was Mesoamerica, the region where North and Central America meet. Among the people living there were the Aztecs (also known as Mexica or Tenocha); they built a complex civilization centered around their great city of Tenochtitlan (modern Mexico City). This was one of the largest cities in the world (with an estimated population of 200,000) and arguably more beautiful and cleaner than most contemporary European capitals.\n \nIn Aztec society, membership in the calpulli established each individual's religious and secular schooling, as well as how they would be trained in warfare. The men of a calpulli served together in battle and on the numerous public works projects. Their soldiers wielded weapons of wood and stone, and they often sought prisoners to be sacrificed in religious ceremonies.</string>
    <string _locid="120098">The Haudenosaunee War Chief is an infantry unit with good hitpoints and a decent ranged attack. This War Chief does most of his damage at range, so it is good to maintain this range whenever possible. His bonus ability gives nearby units more hitpoints.\n \nLike Explorers, the War Chief has a good line of sight and can collect Treasures and build Trading Posts.\n \nIf a War Chief falls in a fight, he collapses and has to generate enough hitpoints to be recovered by allies. A fallen War Chief can also be returned to the Community Plaza by doing the War Ceremony.</string>
    <string _locid="120099">War chiefs, typically young men in their prime, were responsible for leading warriors into battle. Even though they led their tribe's war efforts, they had to answer to a council of tribal leaders who attended to the daily affairs of the tribe.\n \nMohawk chief Thayendenaga, also known as Joseph Brant, fought alongside the British during the American Revolution. Along with his army of Native Americans, he fought in the battle of Oriskany in August 1779. He served as a captain in the British Army until the end of the war, at which point he turned his attentions to diplomacy and working to achieve the best living conditions for his people in the period after the American victory. </string>
    <string _locid="120100">The War Chief is a cavalry unit with good speed and attack, but no range. This means the War Chief is vulnerable to units until he closes in on them. As one of the faster units in the game, this happens quickly. This unit also makes nearby allied warriors move more quickly.\n \nLike Explorers, the War Chief has a good line of sight and can collect Treasures and build Trading Posts.\n \nIf a War Chief falls in a fight, he collapses and has to generate enough hitpoints to be recovered by allies. A fallen War Chief can also be returned to the Community Plaza by doing the War Ceremony.</string>
    <string _locid="120101">War chiefs, typically young men in their prime, were responsible for leading warriors into battle. Even though they led their tribe's war efforts, they had to answer to a council of tribal leaders who attended to the daily affairs of the tribe.\n \nOne of the most renowned war chiefs was Sitting Bull (1831-1890), also known as Tatanka Yotanka. Born in the territory of present-day South Dakota, he was renowned as a Lakota healer and prophet. Sitting Bull led Native resistance against U.S. government attempts to take over tribal lands, which included his involvement in the Battle of the Greasy Grass (also known as the Battle of the Little Bighorn) with his lieutenants Crazy Horse and Gall. After spending several years in Canada with his followers, Sitting Bull returned to the U.S. under a government amnesty program.</string>
    <string _locid="120102">The Spy unit has Stealth ability and a bonus against mercenaries, Explorers, and War Chiefs. It's very useful in military campaigns, particularly as a relatively low-cost infantry unit. Another plus is that Spies can see other Stealth units.</string>
    <string _locid="120103">For as long as there have been presidents and kings, governments have enlisted the aid of individuals for espionage. During the turbulent seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, spies were used by various governments to uncover secrets and identify opportunities for attack. Spies were known to use a variety of tools and technologies, such as invisible ink and secret codes. The fledgling government of the United States of America found itself embroiled in multiple assaults by loyalist spies - including secret messages sent to agents of the crown by William Franklin, Benjamin Franklin's own son!</string>
    <string _locid="120104">The Villager is the main resource gatherer for all Native American Civilizations. Villagers are relatively inexpensive but fragile; they are not meant for combat, but will fire weak muskets to defend themselves and others. Villagers can be used to collect Treasures.\n \nEach Civilization has a limit to the number of Villagers they can have at once. Villagers pay for themselves rather quickly, and the longer an individual Villager is alive, the more he contributes to the overall wealth of a given colony. Some Civilizations may receive Villagers from the Tribal Council, while others have to rely solely on producing them from Town Centers.</string>
    <string _locid="120105">Highly industrious and loyal to a fault, the Villager lives to work for you. Whether it's chopping down the seventeen thousandth tree, scurrying across the map to a distant pile of silver ore, or endlessly toiling away at a mill, the Villager is ready to happily tackle any tedious task. The Villager’s hobbies include running away from enemy soldiers, being thrown into the river by enemy cannon fire, and crochet.</string>
    <string _locid="120106">The Warrior Priest is an infantry unit with a good melee attack. He has the ability to heal nearby units, and counts as two units when occupying the Community Plaza.</string>
    <string _locid="120107">The most densely populated region of the New World in 1492 was Mesoamerica, the region where North and Central America meet. Among the people living there were the Aztecs (also known as Mexica or Tenocha); they built a complex civilization centered around their great city of Tenochtitlan (modern Mexico City). This was one of the largest cities in the world (with an estimated population of 200,000) and arguably more beautiful and cleaner than most contemporary European capitals.\n \nIn Aztec society, membership in the calpulli established each individual's religious and secular schooling, as well as how they would be trained in warfare. The men of a calpulli served together in battle and on the numerous public works projects. Their soldiers wielded weapons of wood and stone, and they often sought prisoners to be sacrificed in religious ceremonies.\n \nThe male children of the upper classes attended a special school called a calmecac. It was there they learned the secrets of the Aztec priesthood and how to perform religious ceremonies and responsibilities - in essence, grooming them for leadership, since in Aztec society government and religion were virtually indistinguishable.</string>
    <string _locid="120108">Advanced Hot Air Balloons are unlocked in the Home City and trained from Explorers. They reveal a huge area, allowing a player to see the units of enemy players from far away.\n \nUnlike regular Hot Air Balloons, Advanced Hot Air Balloons will persist for an entire game.</string>
    <string _locid="120109">During the U.S. Civil War, both the Union and Confederate forces deployed balloons for reconnaissance purposes. Even though their use and efficacy in battle was limited, they did offer a glimpse of the future potential of air power.\n \nIn June of 1861, Thaddeus Lowe rose 500 feet above Washington, D.C. as a demonstration to President Lincoln of the value of balloons. Even though the Enterprise was tethered, the sight of it above the capital impressed Lincoln enough to establish a Balloon Corps for the Union Army. Eventually, Lowe oversaw the construction of seven balloons, six of which actually saw service during the war. All of these balloons used hydrogen gas instead of hot air.</string>
    <string _locid="120110">The Bank Wagon is used to create banks, which generate Coin for your civilization. It is a very expensive building, especially early, when the Food and Wood needed for its construction compete directly with Settler production and researching improvements or constructing buildings. </string>
    <string _locid="120111">Before the completion of the transcontinental railroad in 1869, commerce between the East Coast of the US and its western territories was extremely limited. Choices boiled down to either shipping the goods around South America’s Cape Horn or a land journey across the continent. With the California gold rush in 1849, the opportunities for the reliable transportation of goods and currency increased dramatically.\n \nDuring the 1850s and 1860s, Wells Fargo became known as the premier provider of financial and commercial transport services. Its overland stagecoach line encompassed over 3,000 miles across the west, with routes to California, Montana, Colorado, and Nebraska.\n \nThe coaches used by Wells Fargo were constructed by J. Stephens Abbott and Lewis Downing at their factory in Concord, New Hampshire. They were built tall and wide to better accommodate the less-than-smooth dirt trails available. These wagons used a suspension made from thick bullhide, rather than steel – giving their coaches a remarkably smooth ride.</string>
    <string _locid="120112">The Travois is similar to the Covered Wagon, except that you can use a Travois to immediately create a variety of buildings for free. You can save your Travois until later Ages, and then create more expensive and powerful buildings (such as Estates) without expending resources.\n \nSome travois can only build a specific building.</string>
    <string _locid="120113">For migratory civilizations that didn't use the wheel, the travois provided a handy means of transporting goods and supplies and in some cases the elderly and the sick. A travois was formed by lashing two poles together in the shape of a V with leather crosspieces between them to act as a carrier. The closed end was placed over the shoulders of a person, dog, or horse and then pulled, dragging the open end across the ground.</string>
    <string _locid="120114">Docks can only be built along the shoreline. They train Fishing Boats, Canoes, Caravels, and a number of tougher ships and boats as they become available.\n \nIf your Fishing Boats or Canoes come under attack and you can't fight your enemy off, you can hide your fishing fleet in the Dock. Fishing Boats and Canoes garrisoned in a Dock cannot fish, but they give the Dock the ability to fire on enemy units - so not only are your boats safe, they can defend themselves as well.</string>
    <string _locid="120115">This is where light artillery, such as Falconets, Grenadiers, and Rams are produced in the New World. Artillery are some of the deadliest units available, so if you have built an Artillery Foundry or Siege Workshop, protect it. And if you see an enemy Foundry or Siege Workshop, destroy it!\n \nBecause artillery moves very slowly, it is best to build the Artillery Foundry or Siege Workshop as close to where it is needed as possible. If that is outside your colony, this can make it vulnerable to attacks, so place it carefully.</string>
    <string _locid="120116">The Town Center is the heart of every colony or village. Gatherers are trained here. Shipments from the Tribal Council or Home City arrive here. The improvements that advance your colony through the Ages are here. Town Centers provide population spaces, or slots, for your total population limit. In the Fortress Age, units which can construct new Town Centers become available from the Tribal Council or Home City. The Tribal Council can provide Town Travois to build new Town Centers, while the Home City provides Covered Wagons to build new Town Centers. Both Town Travois and Covered Wagons are available in limited numbers.\n \nIf your town comes under attack, there is a Minutemen button in European Town Centers that drums up the militia for your town's defense. In Native towns, this defense comes from the Call the People Ceremony at the Community Plaza. Both of these measures are for emergencies only, since these fighters aren't meant to be used as regular warriors. There is also a button called the Town Bell that calls all your gatherers to the Town Center to hide from attacks. While inside, the gatherers fire at any attackers nearby. Pressing the Town Bell button again sends your gatherers back to work.</string>
    <string _locid="120117">The villages of Native Americans ranged in size from a couple of extended family units, to the much larger cities of Mesoamerica.\n \nThe tribes of the North American plains, whose livelihood depended on following the migration of the buffalo, were primarily nomadic. As such, their villages and shelters consisted of Teepees and other structures that could be quickly disassembled and easily transported. The Teepees of the Lakota Nation were made of buffalo hide and then decorated with paintings depicting the daily life and dreams of their people.\n \nIn Mesoamerica the Aztecs constructed great cities, most notably Tenochtitlan on the site of modern Mexico City. Described by some early Spanish as grander than most European cities, Tenochtitlan's advanced infrastructure included temples, markets, canals, and even schools.\n \nIn Northeastern North America, the Haudenosaunee inhabited villages built from timber and other forest materials. Individual and extended families lived in communal longhouses. Religious and political matters were discussed in a central longhouse. The longhouse is a symbol for the Haudenosaunee Confederacy, with the Mohawk considered the keepers of the eastern door and the Seneca, the keepers of the western door. In between them, east to west, were the Oneida, Onondaga, Cayuga, and eventually the Tuscarora out of North Carolina. At the centrally located village of Onondaga, the Grand Council Fire burned continually.</string>
    <string _locid="120118">The Corral is the home for cavalry units and the improvements that increase the amount of damage they can sustain and inflict. Groups of up to five units can be trained at once from the Corral. You can train as many units as you can afford, but each additional group stacks up behind the first.\n \nCorrals are relatively inexpensive, so you may want to build an additional Corral to produce units faster or improve your warriors more quickly.</string>
    <string _locid="120119">A corral is a building in which horses are housed. Horses provided the American Indians with speed and mobility, particularly during battle and when hunting large game such as buffalo.\n \nAfter an extended period of absence from the Western Hemisphere, the horse was reintroduced to the New World in the 1500s by the Spanish. As horses spread across the continent, the Plains Indians in particular became known for their skills as riders and horse breeders.</string>
    <string _locid="120121">Gatherers working on a Farm provide a steady stream of Food to your village. Building a Farm costs a lot of Wood, so Farms are often built later in games when nearby hunting has been exhausted, or when a player wants to keep gatherers near the safety of the Camp Circle. Gathering Food from a Farm begins slowly; but with improvements, a Farm can become a very efficient source of Food. Only a limited number of gatherers can work at each Farm.</string>
    <string _locid="120122">The Native Americans were well versed in various agricultural techniques. Sharing their expertise with the Mayflower colonists helped ensure the colony's survival. Adaptation of agriculture among Indian Nations depended largely on usefulness and location.\n \nThe Aztecs, with their home city of Tenochtitlan, engineered extremely complex systems of farming, producing crop yields capable of supporting a population of several hundred thousand people.\n \nThe Haudenosaunee were accomplished growers of fruits and vegetables. They referred to their three primary crops - corn, beans, and squash - as "The Three Sisters."\n \nThe ancestors of the Lakota and other Plains Indians were farmers as well as hunters, but their descendants adopted a more nomadic buffalo-based way of life after being forced westward by the advance of the Europeans.</string>
    <string _locid="120123">The Community Plaza is where your Villagers gather together to provide different benefits for your civilization.  If you direct a Villager to a Community Plaza, the Villager will automatically begin a chosen ceremony.\n \nThe more Villagers you have occupying the Community Plaza, the more effective the ceremony.\n \nEach ceremony helps your civilization in different ways.  For example, a Harvest Ceremony enables your civilization to create units faster, while other ceremonies can be used to improve your explorer or create military units.</string>
    <string _locid="120124">Since time immemorial, Indigenous Peoples have inhabited North America, Mesoamerica, and South America.\n \nWhen European settlers first arrived in the Americas, there were an estimated ten million Native inhabitants in North America alone, speaking more than 300 different languages. Some were nomadic like the Lakota who followed the bison across the Great Plains. Others were sedentary like the Haudenosaunee of the Northeast Woodlands who, along with the Aztec (Mexico) and Inca (Peru), built permanent settlements and grew staple crops.\n \nOne thing that the Indigenous Peoples of the Americas shared was a strong sense of community—working together and sharing natural resources. The Community Plaza is a symbolic representation of these interdependent communities of the Indigenous Peoples of the Americas.</string>
    <string _locid="120125">Aztec Houses are necessary to support the expanding population of a growing empire. Most units that you can train take up a specific amount of population spaces or population slots. Each Aztec House or Town Center that you build raises the number of slots you have available, allowing you to train more and more units. There is a limit on the number of Aztec Houses you can build in a single game.\n \nEvery time you train a unit, the game checks to see if you have enough Aztec Houses to support the new soldiers or civilians. If you do not, you will not be able to train the units until you build an Aztec House or Town Center.</string>
    <string _locid="120126">Houses in the New World displayed varying styles, from the Cape-style houses of New England to the claim shanties in the West to the ranch houses of Texas and Mexico. Often the house style reflected the cultural heritage of the people who settled the land.\n \nFor life in their relatively dry climate, the Aztec built their homes as simple structures made from adobe (a mixture of water and dirt), with a thatched roof.</string>
    <string _locid="120127">The Haudenosaunee Longhouse supports a population space of 15 and offers the Woodland Dwellers improvement.  For a cost of 500 Food and 500 Coin, Woodland Dwellers improvement provides your colony just over 100 Wood for every minute of the game.</string>
    <string _locid="120128">Houses in the New World displayed varying styles, from the Cape-style houses of New England to the claim shanties in the West to the ranch houses of Texas and Mexico. Often the house style reflected the cultural heritage of the people who settled the land.\n \nThe Haudenosaunee of the Northeastern forests lived in longhouses. These communal dwellings had frame structures covered with elm bark and averaged about 60 feet long and 18 feet wide.</string>
    <string _locid="120129">The Native Embassy allows you to train Native warriors. Native Embassies are not required to be allied with Native civilizations and are allowed to be built near their Town Centers. European, Asian and American civilizations are required to be allied with a Native civilization to train their warriors at the Embassy.</string>
    <string _locid="120130">Establishing an embassy is more than simply erecting a building. An embassy represents one civilization or country formally respecting and acknowledging the legitimacy of another. Embassies serve as powerful symbols in the overall context of how societies conduct business, trade, and sometimes war.</string>
    <string _locid="120131">The Nobles Hut is a more powerful version of the War Hut, with extra hitpoints and a higher attack. It's also where the military units of the Aztec ruling classes are trained: the Aztec Knights. You can access these warriors in the third Age.</string>
    <string _locid="120132">In Aztec society, membership in the calpulli established each individual's religious and secular schooling, as well as how they would be trained in warfare. The men of a calpulli served together in battle and on the numerous public works projects. Their soldiers wielded weapons of wood and stone, and they often sought prisoners to be sacrificed in religious ceremonies.\n \nThe male children of the upper classes attended a special school called a calmecac. It was there they learned the secrets of the Aztec priesthood and how to perform religious ceremonies and responsibilities - in essence, grooming them for leadership, since in Aztec society government and religion were virtually indistinguishable.</string>
    <string _locid="120133">The Saloon is a building that not only provides a great place to hang out and discuss current events, but also generates mercenaries and outlaws that you can use to build up your forces. Age of Empires III: Definitive Edition offers three new mercenaries to further expand your military options: Fusiliers, Elmeti, and Ninjas.</string>
    <string _locid="120134">Taverns, Inns, and Public Houses (a.k.a. Pubs) have a long and colorful history across Europe and North America. While the term Saloon commonly refers to establishments associated with the American Old West, businesses where local townsfolk gather to consume alcohol and discuss the issues of the day have existed for centuries.\n \nThe common denominator, of course, is the ready availability of alcohol, noted for its ability to loosen the tongue and inflame passions. The future course of nations was most often argued and planned within such walls. From Paul Revere to Wild Bill Hickock, the day's movers and shakers typically gathered in a local watering hole.</string>
    <string _locid="120135">Unlike Houses, Teepees do not increase your population limit (the Lakota start with a 200 population limit). Lakota military units that are in the proximity of a Teepee get additional hitpoints. Build them around your town to strengthen your warriors on defense.</string>
    <string _locid="120136">Houses in the New World displayed varying styles, from the Cape-style houses of New England to the claim shanties in the West to the ranch houses of Texas and Mexico. Often the house style reflected the cultural heritage of the people who settled the land.\n \nTo meet the needs of a nomadic people living on the Great Plains, the Lakota Nation developed the Teepee as their basic structure for shelter. Early explorers were impressed by the Teepee and its effectiveness against the elements.</string>
    <string _locid="120137">The War Hut is the home for infantry units and the improvements that will increase the amount of damage these units can take and dish out. Because War Huts are relatively inexpensive, you may want to build an additional War Hut dedicated to improving soldiers or more rapidly producing units.</string>
    <string _locid="120138">In both North American and Mesoamerican cultures, warriors were critical to the defense and survival of the tribe.\n \nOn the Great Plains, warrior societies emerged - complete with their own dances, songs, and costumes. Prestige was typically bestowed based on an individual's acts of courage during battle, such acts as stealing weapons, horses, and counting coup.\n \nIn Aztec society, membership in the calpulli established each individual's religious and secular schooling, as well as how they would be trained in warfare. The men of a calpulli served together in battle and on the numerous public works projects. The Aztec soldiers wielded weapons of wood and stone, and they often sought prisoners to be sacrificed in religious ceremonies.\n \nFor the Haudenosaunee, the longhouse stood as the central symbol of religious and civic life. In fact, the name they call themselves - Haudenosaunee - means "People of the Long House." It was in the longhouse that the Grand Council of the six member nations of the Haudenosaunee Confederacy made decisions regarding matters of war and peace.</string>
    <string _locid="120139">This building holds resources. In order to collect them, you must destroy the building. Any unit that can attack buildings can attack the Huari Stronghold, but only a gatherer can collect the resources.\n \nHistory:\n \nThis Huari Stronghold contains supplies, but you will have to destroy the building to get them.\n \nThe Inca learned many architectural lessons from the Huari, including terracing techniques that turned sloped fields into useful agricultural land. The Huari had a large system of roads in their mountainous country that the Inca's are thought to have incorporated into their own.</string>
    <string _locid="120140">This building holds resources. In order to collect them, you must destroy the building. Any unit that can attack buildings can attack the Huari Stronghold, but only a gatherer can collect the resources.\n \nHistory:\n \nThis Huari Stronghold contains supplies, but you will have to destroy the building to get them.\n \nThe Inca learned many architectural lessons from the Huari, including terracing techniques that turned sloped fields into useful agricultural land. The Huari had a large system of roads in their mountainous country which the Inca's are thought to have incorporated into their own.</string>
    <string _locid="120141">The Travois is similar to the Covered Wagon, except that you can use a Travois to immediately create any building available to the Haudenosaunee during the current Age, other than Trading Posts or Town Centers. This lets you create a variety of buildings on demand. Or you can save your Travois until later Ages, and then create more expensive and powerful buildings (such as Estates) without expending resources.\n \nHistory:\n \nFor migratory civilizations that didn't use the wheel, the travois provided a handy means of transporting goods and supplies and in some cases the elderly and the sick. A travois was formed by lashing two poles together in the shape of a V with leather crosspieces between them to act as a carrier. The closed end was placed over the shoulders of a person, dog, or horse and then pulled, dragging the open end across the ground.</string>
    <string _locid="120142">The Travois is similar to the Covered Wagon, except that you can use this Travois to immediately create a Farm for free.\n \nHistory:\n \nFor migratory civilizations that didn't use the wheel, the travois provided a handy means of transporting goods and supplies and in some cases the elderly and the sick. A travois was formed by lashing two poles together in the shape of a V with leather crosspieces between them to act as a carrier. The closed end was placed over the shoulders of a person, dog, or horse and then pulled, dragging the open end across the ground.</string>
    <string _locid="120143">The Travois is similar to the Covered Wagon, except that you can use this Travois to immediately create a Nobles Hut for free.\n \nHistory:\n \nFor migratory civilizations that didn't use the wheel, the travois provided a handy means of transporting goods and supplies and in some cases the elderly and the sick. A travois was formed by lashing two poles together in the shape of a V with leather crosspieces between them to act as a carrier. The closed end was placed over the shoulders of a person, dog, or horse and then pulled, dragging the open end across the ground.</string>
    <string _locid="120144">The Travois is similar to the Covered Wagon, except that you can use this Travois to immediately create a Trading Post for free.\n \nHistory:\n \nFor migratory civilizations that didn't use the wheel, the travois provided a handy means of transporting goods and supplies and in some cases the elderly and the sick. A travois was formed by lashing two poles together in the shape of a V with leather crosspieces between them to act as a carrier. The closed end was placed over the shoulders of a person, dog, or horse and then pulled, dragging the open end across the ground.</string>
    <string _locid="120145">The Travois is similar to the Covered Wagon, except that you can use this Travois to immediately create a War Hut for free.\n \nHistory:\n \nFor migratory civilizations that didn't use the wheel, the travois provided a handy means of transporting goods and supplies and in some cases the elderly and the sick. A travois was formed by lashing two poles together in the shape of a V with leather crosspieces between them to act as a carrier. The closed end was placed over the shoulders of a person, dog, or horse and then pulled, dragging the open end across the ground.</string>
    <string _locid="120146">The Petard Nitro is a small explosive device, primarily used at close range to break down walls and other defensive structures. It is more powerful than the regular Petard. They're relatively inexpensive, and you'll find them very useful in siege attacks.\n \nHistory:\n \nThe term petard first emerged during medieval times, referring to a small and notoriously unstable explosive device similar in concept and usage to the modern grenade. The name probably derives from the Latin "petar," which means, "to break wind" (an example of the military mind's wry sense of humor.)\n \nTo be "hoisted by one's own petard" is a phrase commonly thought to mean something along the lines of "being hung with your own rope"; or, to stay true to the actual context of an explosive device, to be blown up by your own bomb. The saying is derived from Shakespeare's Hamlet. The bard wrote:\n \n"For 'tis the sport to have the engineer\nHoist with his own petar"</string>
    <string _locid="120147">The longest mountain chain on the planet, the Andes range stretches from Venezuela to Argentina - over 4000 miles long. A relatively new mountain range, the Andes first formed during the Cretaceous period about 140 million years ago.\n \nThe Andes encompass nearly the entire West coast of South America. As such, the mountain range manifests a broad range of climates and geography. Near the equator, the mountains have a warm and humid climate, with tropical rainforests practically lying in their shadow. To the south towards Antarctica, the Andes range is colder and more glacial.\n \nProbably the most well-known of the indigenous peoples to inhabit the Andes were the Inca, whose empire was based in the area of modern-day Peru from the early 1300s to 1533. At the height of their expansion, the Inca ruled over much of western South America. The conquistador Francisco Pizarro established Spanish rule in 1533, when he oversaw the death of the last Inca emperor.</string>
    <string _locid="120148">Amidst the towering peaks of the Andes lies a region within modern-day Chile known as Araucania. It is a land of angry volcanoes, mighty rivers, and hundreds of emerald lagoons. The resilient Mapuche people have lived here for generations, holding fast to their culture and traditions against the onslaught of the Spanish and others.\n \nThe Andes frame the west coast of Araucania, sheltering the inner central valley from the effects of the Pacific Ocean. Eagerly sought after by the Spanish, this central valley provided the bulk of this land’s agrarian economy. For over 100 years, the Mapuche successfully defended this land against Spanish attempts at conquest.\n \nAfter Spanish tenure in the region, the Mapuche faced years of additional assaults by the governments of Chile and Argentina. In 1860, the Mapuche selected a French lawyer named Orelie-Antoine Tounens to be King of Araucania (also called New France), and established their own government, flag, and coinage. Chile and Argentina refused to accept Tounens and had him deported several times. He died in France in 1878, stripped of his crown and any authority.</string>
    <string _locid="120149">Rich in history, resources, and opportunity, California has inspired generations of settlers, entrepreneurs, and would-be conquerors. With its majestic northern redwood forests, fertile central valley, magnificent coastline, and sun-drenched deserts, California represents a vibrant, passionate dream.\n \nFor thousands of years, California was home to a multitude of indigenous peoples: among those in the north were the Modoc, Pomo, and Shasta tribes; the central valley was home to the Yokuts, Paiute, and other tribes; the Chumash and other peoples lived in the coastal regions; the Yuma and Mohave in the southern desert regions. It is estimated that well over 300,000 people inhabited California prior to the arrival of the Europeans.\n \nIn 1542, Juan Rodriquez Cabrillo landed on the California coast and claimed it for Spain. Several years later in 1579, Sir Francis Drake arrived to make very much the same claim for the British Crown. The tug-of-war between European powers, Mexico, and eventually the United States over California continued until 1848 when the U.S. finally established its control over the territory. With the discovery of gold in 1848 and the gold rush starting in 1849, a fresh tidal wave of humanity poured into the state, with all the predictable consequences of hope, pain, gain, and loss. The net result for the original Native American inhabitants: probably two-thirds lost due to warfare, disease, and not-so-benign neglect.</string>
    <string _locid="120150">Hispaniola is the second-biggest island of the West Indies, with the nations of Haiti located on the western third of the island and the Dominican Republic to the east. Its humid, tropical climate offers a nourishing environment to a wide array of plants and animals. With its rugged mountain ranges, coastal beaches, grassland savannas, and pine forests, Hispaniola provides an ever-changing panoply of environments and scenic backdrops.\n \nFor thousands of years, Native peoples thrived on Hispaniola. When Christopher Columbus arrived in 1492, he was welcomed by the Taino Indians. Peaceful and generous, they were quite cooperative with the first Europeans - much to their eventual regret. Subsequent waves of Europeans repaid the Taino’s generosity with slavery and exploitation.\n \nIn 1493, the Spanish founded the first European settlement on Hispaniola: Isabella. It was but a short distance from the Cibao Valley and its much-desired deposits of gold. More gold was discovered on the south of the island, and the city of Santo Domingo was built nearby soon afterwards in 1496. It is estimated that within twenty-five years of the Spanish arrival, the Taino population had fallen from several million to approximately 50,000, from disease, warfare, and the slave trade.</string>
    <string _locid="120151">Stretching over 2,400 kilometers, the Orinoco River is one of South America’s largest waterways. Discovered by Christopher Columbus during his third voyage to the Americas in 1498, the Orinoco River basin covers 880,000 square kilometers across Venezuela and Colombia. The headwaters of the Orinoco were not mapped until the 1950s, however.\n \nThe Orinoco delta is home to the Warao people, whose name translates as “people of the water” - an apt description as the river basin offers substantial fish and wildlife resources. Manatee, river otter, parrots, catfish, and many other types of fauna are found in this land, where the ebb and flow of river and earth have continued unabated across generations. Humid, tropical, lush with life in abundance, the Orinoco region is to this day an example of a world primeval.</string>
    <string _locid="120152">The Northwest Territory is a land of cool, lush rainforests, magnificent mountain ranges, high desert plains, rocky coastlines, and rivers teeming with salmon.\n \nLong before Lewis and Clark began their arduous and remarkable journey across the North American continent in the nineteenth century, the upper Northwest corner had been home to a diverse blend of Native American cultures. With its moderate climate and extensive natural resources, the Northwest offered a rich environment within which many different tribal nations could develop and flourish, including the Nootka, Haida, Quinault, Makah, Puyallup, Tlingit, Tsimshian, and Snohomish.\n \nEven with its abundant resources (including timber, fur, and fishing), the region remained relatively ignored throughout much of the 1800s, with probably no more than a couple thousand U.S. settlers and maybe 30,000 Native Americans. John Jacob Astor and the Hudson’s Bay Company both established trading companies in the area during the early half of the nineteenth century. Yet the Northwest remained fairly remote until gold was discovered in the Yukon in 1890. The resulting influx of treasure hunters transformed Seattle from a backwater seaport to a bustling, metropolitan city.</string>
    <string _locid="120153">Referred to by the Spanish as “el Desierto Pintura,” the Painted Desert has dazzled visitors for thousands of years. With its multicolored bluffs, mesas, and petrified forests, the Painted Desert offers a kaleidoscope of ever-shifting shapes and colors. This natural wonder encompasses over 93,000 acres of Arizona lands.\n \nArcheologists have found evidence that people have lived in this region for nearly 10,000 years. The climate was cooler during the period immediately following the last ice age, and the region’s habitat included large mammals such as bison. Over time, however, average temperatures increased, transforming the area into a more arid and desert environment.\n \nEven with the climate change, the Painted Desert has remained the home of many Native peoples over the centuries. Petroglyphs and artifacts such as pottery and flint spear points provide clues to their lifestyles and culture. The Pueblo peoples particularly were known for their expertise in farming and weaving and they traded these goods extensively with neighboring tribes.</string>
    <string _locid="120154">Explorers, wanderers, and nomads travel great distances uncertain how the journey will end. Will it end in prosperity or poverty? Fame, death, sadness or glory?\n \nFind out what lies beyond the horizon...</string>
    <string _locid="120077">A cache of resources that gatherers can collect very quickly. Crates of Food, Cords of Wood, and Chests of Coin are generally delivered from the Home City or Tribal Council to Town Centers or other buildings. They provide resources very quickly, but in a very limited amount. Any player can gather from any crate, which means allies can share them or enemies can steal them if they are left unattended at a Town Center. Guard crates carefully, or better yet, use them as soon as possible!</string>
    <string _locid="120155">This animal can be fished for Coin by gatherers - units like Fishing Boats, Caravels, and Canoes.</string>
    <string _locid="120156">This animal can be fished for Food by gatherers such as Fishing Boats, Caravels, and Canoes.</string>
    <string _locid="120157">This predator is guarding a Treasure. In order to collect the Treasure, which may be resources, experience points, or even Villagers or soldiers, the predator or predators guarding it must be killed or tamed. Any unit can attack a Treasure guardian, but only Explorers, War Chiefs, Villagers and Settlers can collect the Treasure. War Chiefs may choose to use their Animal Friendship ability to tame the animal guardians instead of killing them.</string>
    <string _locid="120158">These herdable animals can be hunted for Food by gatherers - Coureur des Bois, Cree Coureurs, Settlers, Settler Wagons, and Villagers. Unlike wild animals, these animals can be captured and sent back to your town. If they are alone traveling back to your town, another player may stumble across them and steal them away from you.\n \nHerdable animals "fatten" over time, so the longer they are alive, the more Food they will provide when your gatherers finally hunt them. They will fatten even faster at a Livestock Pen or Farm.</string>
    <string _locid="120159">This animal can be hunted for Food by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.</string>
    <string _locid="120160">This ore deposit can be mined for Coin by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs</string>
    <string _locid="120161">This tree can be chopped down for Wood by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.</string>
    <string _locid="120162">This berry bush provides Food when any gatherer works on it - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs. The Food is slow and limited, but safe to collect since the bushes often grow near Town Centers.</string>
    <string _locid="120163">Scientific Name: Lobodon carcinophagus\nApprox. Size: up to 7 feet in length and over 500 pounds\nDiet: Krill\n \nThe Crabeater Seal lives in the Southern Hemisphere, inhabiting the islands, ice packs, and ice floes that surround the Antarctic. They have also been found on the southern coasts of South Africa, South America, New Zealand, and Australia. An extremely successful species, some estimate that over half of all seals in the world are Crabeaters. They can grow up to 7 feet long and weigh over 500 pounds.\n \nThe name “Crabeater” is somewhat of a misnomer, as this seal's primary diet consists of krill - small, shrimp-like crustaceans that represent a key food source for many other sea creatures, such as sharks, baleen whales, and manta rays. The Crabeater’s teeth have been uniquely adapted to strain large quantities of krill from seawater.</string>
    <string _locid="120164">Scientific Name: Lama guanicoe\nApprox. Size: 35 to 51 inches at the shoulder; 200 lb.\nDiet: Grasses, vegetation\n \nThe guanaco is an undomesticated relative of the South American llama, found on the plains and mountains of Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Paraguay, and Peru. The wild population of this mammal is estimated at about 600,000.\n \nCovered with a thick coat of long, soft, reddish-tan hair, a full-grown male stands 35 to 51 inches high at the shoulder and can weigh as much as 200 pounds. Its head is small, with pointed ears; the neck is long, with a graceful curve; and the legs are long and slender. The fur on the belly is pure white. It feeds on grasses and vegetation.\n \nGuanacos are fast-running animals, but become careless due to their innate curiosity and often fall victim to wary predators. The guanaco is also a strong swimmer and takes to water readily.</string>
    <string _locid="120165">Mined and used for thousands of years, copper has been found in countries across the globe - Chile, Indonesia, Australia, Russia, China, and the U.S. Ancient civilizations used copper for mirrors, jewelry, weapons, even plumbing.\n \nCopper was initially gathered from surface deposits found on ore outcroppings. Early miners eventually burrowed deeper, following the veins underground. Egyptians excavated shafts over 30 meters deep in search of the metal. The first smelting furnaces date back to nearly 5000 BCE.\n \nTin and copper were alloyed to create a stronger and more durable metal: bronze. As tin and copper were typically not found together, the need for both metals led to increased trade and commerce among ancient peoples. Today, bronze alloys are composed of approximately 60% copper and 40% tin.\n \nMalleable and versatile, copper today is used for a multitude of products, including wiring, plumbing, roofing materials, and integrated circuits.</string>
    <string _locid="120166">As is the case with copper, people have gathered and mined tin for thousands of years. Its key value to the ancient world was in combination with copper, the creation of bronze - an alloy widely used for weaponry and art.\n \nBecause of its ability to inhibit corrosion, tin has long been used to coat steel and other metals. Indeed, the commonly referred to “tin can” is actually made from steel, with only a minimal tin plating.\n \nEven though scarce, tin is found all over the world and on every continent. Most tin processed today is mined in Southeast Asia.</string>
    <string _locid="120167">The Andes is home to numerous different plants and animals, many of which have played a key role in the lives of the people who live there.\n \nFor example, the wild potato has been cultivated for over 7,000 years, and serves as a vital foodstuff on the high plateaus where it is too cold to grow wheat or maize. Francisco Pizarro brought the potato back to Europe after his conquest of Peru.\n \nAn endangered tree once vital to the Inca is the polyepis, a species related to the rose. An evergreen with red, thick bark, the polyepis has been used for centuries for construction, firewood, and even medicine.</string>
    <string _locid="120168">The native forests of Araucania are composed primarily of Southern beeches and the Aracauria tree. Their numbers have been reduced through extensive logging over the past few centuries, and today the forests include a greater percentage of pines and eucalyptus.\n \nThe Aracauria tree (scientific name: araucaria araucana) is native to this region. It is extremely adaptable to temperate climates, however, and has been transplanted as far away as Great Britain and Canada. The Aracauria is a conifer and can reach a height of over 100 feet tall. The seeds of the tree can be eaten and have a taste akin to pine nuts. In Great Britain, the tree was nicknamed “Monkey Puzzle” due to its unusually dense branch structure.</string>
    <string _locid="120169">Home to many different plant species, one of the most spectacular and well known is the California redwood. Redwoods are found along the coasts of northern California and southern Oregon. Extremely long-lived, some of these mighty trees have survived over two thousand years. Perhaps the tallest tree on earth, redwoods can grow to nearly 400 feet tall.</string>
    <string _locid="120170">If you’re looking for a prime example of Northwest vegetation, the Hoh Rainforest offers a spectacular and almost mystical setting. One of the world’s few temperate rainforests, there you’ll encounter luxurious stands of Sitka spruce, western hemlock, red cedar, and Douglas fir. Underfoot you’ll wander through lush expanses of mosses, ferns, and lichens. Meandering through this natural wonderland is the Hoh River itself - Hoh means “fast moving water” to the local Native Americans, and indeed with the seasonal rains, this river invariably overruns its banks as it has done again and again throughout millennia.</string>
    <string _locid="120171">Even though an arid region, the Painted Desert is home to many different types of plants and animals. The Yucca family is well represented, with their white blossoms and spiky leaves. You’ll also find different species of cacti, mosses, and lichens throughout the region. The landscape includes native grasses such as the Galleta and Blue Grama, both adapted to the windswept, dry climate. And if you come during the right time of year, you’ll see the desert bloom with several varieties of wildflowers, offering a welcome collage of seasonal color.</string>
    <string _locid="120172">Nathaniel attacks with a rifle and tomahawk. He has a lot of hitpoints and two special ranged attacks, Hawkeye Attack and Eagle Eye, that he can use once every couple of minutes. If he falls in a fight, he collapses and has to regenerate enough health to be recovered by allies. Nathaniel can collect Treasures and build Trading Posts near Native settlements and Trade Routes.</string>
    <string _locid="120173">Raised by his Haudenosaunee mother Nonahkee and uncle Ká:nien, Nathaniel helped unite several Haudenosaunee villages into a confederation of shared interests and economy. But the rising conflict between the American colonists and the British forces him, and others, to choose sides. As the continent descends into war, under whose banner will Nathaniel's wits and courage be tested?</string>
    <string _locid="120174">General Washington attacks with his officer’s saber. He has a lot of hitpoints, but if he falls in a fight, he collapses and has to regenerate enough health to be recovered by allies. Washington can collect Treasures, but cannot build Trading Posts.</string>
    <string _locid="120175">The only U.S. President elected unanimously, George Washington stands tall in history as one of America’s greatest leaders. A Virginian landowner and farmer, General Washington understood well both the sword and the plowshare.\n \nAs a general, Washington was greatly admired by those who served under him. Never one to remain on the sidelines, he led the charge into action time and time again. During the French and Indian War, Washington survived many battles, even having a horse shot out from under him on two occasions.\n \nAs commander in chief of the Continental army, Washington faced the great challenge of maintaining his troops’ morale during the bitter winter at Valley Forge. </string>
    <string _locid="120176">Colonel Kuechler attacks with his officer's saber. He has a lot of hitpoints, but if he falls in a fight, he collapses and has to regenerate enough health to be recovered by allies. The Colonel can collect Treasures, but cannot build Trading Posts.</string>
    <string _locid="120177">Colonel Sven Kuechler prides himself on his strict adherence to Hessian military virtues. Discipline. Obedience. Ruthlessness. There's nothing "soft" about Kuechler's leadership. His job is to extinguish this traitorous rebellion firmly and decisively. And none shall stand in his way for long.</string>
    <string _locid="120178">Chayton attacks with a rifle and saber. He has a lot of hitpoints and two special ranged attacks, Hawkeye Attack and Eagle Eye, that he can use once every couple of minutes. If he falls in a fight, he collapses and has to regenerate enough health to be recovered by allies. Chayton can collect Treasures and build Trading Posts near Native settlements and Trade Routes.</string>
    <string _locid="120179">Nathaniel's grandson, Chayton Black, seems to have inherited his family's tendency to wind up smack dab in the middle of opposing forces. Against a backdrop of greed, fear, and prejudice, Chayton rediscovers his Lakota heritage, and realizes that he must take a stand for what is right.</string>
    <string _locid="120180">Billy Holme attacks with a pistol. He has the ability to train a posse of Renegados as if he were a moving Saloon. Holme has a lot of hitpoints, but if he falls in a fight, he collapses and has to regenerate enough health to be recovered by allies. Holme can collect Treasures, but cannot build Trading Posts.</string>
    <string _locid="120181">Sworn to preserve and protect, Sheriff Holme sees this territory as a land of conflict and opportunity. He's a survivor - a tour of duty during the Civil War has given him a gruff, sometimes jesting, view of life. With his long-time friend Chayton by his side, Holme is not a man to let events simply unfold for themselves.</string>
    <string _locid="120182">General Custer attacks with his officer’s saber. He has a lot of hitpoints, but if he falls in a fight, he collapses and has to regenerate enough health to be recovered by allies. Custer cannot collect Treasures or build Trading Posts.</string>
    <string _locid="120183">Impulsive. Proud. Witty. Tragic. While he'll always be remembered for that fateful day at the Little Bighorn river, Custer's life was paradoxical. A fierce warrior who thrived on conflict; a devoted husband adored by his wife; a failed leader who led his men to destruction.\n \nCuster clearly loved the western frontier and reveled in his role in shaping it. Nevertheless, as with any historical figure, the drama of his life and its final act remain clouded in legend.</string>
    <string _locid="120184">This weapons cache is just asking to be blown up. Where is a wagon carrying an unstable load of black powder when you need it?\n \nHistory:\n \nAmmo Storehouses (also known as an ammunition depots or ammo dumps) are used to store military explosives and ammunition. Because these materials are extremely dangerous, an Ammo Storehouse typically has safeguards to prevent unauthorized use and accidental detonation. These measures often involve the use of armed guards, fencing, and a buffer zone surrounding the storehouse. Ammo Storehouses require continuous monitoring, as many explosives tend to degrade and become more unstable over time. </string>
    <string _locid="120185">This bakery sells wagons of food. Will Nathaniel's dwindling family fortune buy enough to feed the soldiers wintering at Valley Forge?\n \nHistory:\n \nOnce popularly referred to as the “Staff of Life,” bread has played a key dietary role for nearly 10,000 years of human history. Originally, bread was unleavened and formed by combining several different grains, grinding them into a powder (flour), adding water to make dough, and then adding heat to cook the mix. Over time, the technology of grinding flour advanced - from hand pestle and mortar to circular stone wheels to watermills. Breads and pastries have spread to every culture in every corner of the world.\n \nBread and politics have long gone hand in hand. In BCE 40, the Roman leadership ruled that rations of bread should be given freely to all adult men. During the Middle Ages, Bakers’ Guilds emerged to better protect bakers from exploitation by the local nobility. And the archetypal (and mythic) example would be the legendary line falsely attributed to Marie Antoinette, “let them eat cake.” The actual quote in French is “Qu’ils mangent de la brioche,” which actually translates to something like “let them eat expensive egg-based pastry.”</string>
    <string _locid="120186">A charming wooden barn. It smells of hay and livestock.\n \nHistory:\n \nBefore the emergence of modern agri-business, managing a farm was primarily a family affair that involved everyone. The center of the family unit was the house, but the business center of the farm was almost certainly the barn.  Typically built from wood and/or stone, the barn served multiple purposes: housing animals, sheltering farm equipment (such as plows), and storing feed. The classic “red” barn came into being primarily due to ready access to ferric oxide (rust) – a common and cheap ingredient for paint. The red barn remains a classic symbol of rural America.</string>
    <string _locid="120187">This wagon is laden with explosives and arms. Unstable and volatile, it will explode if it is run into a Weapons Cache.\n \nHistory:\n \nBlack powder (or gunpowder) is believed to have been first discovered by the Chinese sometime around the ninth century. With proper ingredients and proportions, black powder is actually quite easy to make: 75% saltpeter, 15% charcoal, and 10% sulfur. All three ingredients are fairly easy to locate or manufacture.\n \nHaving ready access to the ingredients necessary for making gunpowder was critical to the eventual success of the U.S. colonies during the American Revolution. In the U.S., up until the 1870s much of the saltpeter (potassium nitrate) used to make black powder was mined from caves in the Appalachian Mountains.</string>
    <string _locid="120188">Kuechler will be using this bridge to cross the Hudson River unless you destroy it. If you destroy it, Kuechler will be delayed and his soldiers will have to cross the river further north.\n \nHistory:\n \nBridges constructed of boats (also known as pontoon bridges or floating bridges) have existed for centuries. The Greek and Roman armies and many other militaries throughout history have utilized such bridges in their far-flung conquests. One method for forming such a bridge would involve lashing boats together, fastening them to both sides of the waterway, and using wooden planks or timbers as a walkway over which troops could cross.</string>
    <string _locid="120189">Nathaniel is using this fire to trick General Cornwallis into thinking the Colonials have made camp in Trenton.\n \nHistory:\n \nSignal fires are an ancient method of communication over long distances. A large structure of wood, usually built on the peak of a hill or mountain, would be lit and then guarded in watches by soldiers who kept the fire burning. Signal fires were used in the New World, often when hostilities broke out.\n \nA legendary signal fire sent Paul Revere on his ride from Boston to Lexington, though the signal Revere saw was simply a single lamp in the steeple of the Old North Church, not a raging bonfire.</string>
    <string _locid="120190">Chief Brave Wolf is expected at the War Council. Take him to the Town Center. If an Brave Wolf falls in a fight, he collapses and has to generate enough hitpoints to be recovered by allies.\n \nHistory:\n \nChief Brave Wolf fought alongside Chief Sitting Bull at the Battle of the Greasy Grass (also known as the Battle of the Little Bighorn).  He was also known as a “contrary.” Sometimes referred to “Sacred Clowns,” and considered epecially chosen by the spirits, contraries used humor and eccentric behavior as part of their ritual. After surrendering to U.S. forces in April, 1877, Chief Brave Wolf enlisted with the U.S. Army under General Nelson A. Miles.</string>
    <string _locid="120191">Chief Bull Bear is expected at the War Council. Take him to the Town Center. If Bull Bear falls in a fight, he collapses and has to generate enough hitpoints to be recovered by allies.\n \nHistory:\n \nDuring the Battle of the Greasy Grass (also known as the Battle of the Little Bighorn), Chief Bull Bear led his fellow Cheyenne Dog Soldiers alongside Chief Gall. The Dog Soldiers (also referred to as the Dog Men Society or Hotamitaneo) were one of several elite Cheyenne military societies. Each society had special training and its own set of symbols and rituals – such as riding into battle with three sacred arrows. The tradition of the Dog Soldier continues to this day. Indeed, Cheyenne Dog Soldiers served with the U.S. military during such conflicts as World War II, Korea, and Vietnam.</string>
    <string _locid="120192">Chief Two Moon is expected at the War Council. Take him to the Town Center. If an Two Moon falls in a fight, he collapses and has to generate enough hitpoints to be recovered by allies.\n \nHistory:\n \nChief Two Moon (also known as Ish i eyo nis si) was a member of the Kit Fox Warrior society and as such fought against Custer at Little Bighorn. Later, after the Battle of Wolf Mountain, Two Moon surrendered to General Nelson A. Miles at Fort Keogh in 1877. Two Moon negotiated a treaty with U.S. forces, and it’s said he even paid a visit to Washington, D.C., and it is said he left quite a positive impression. Indeed, the U.S. Mint acknowledges that Chief Two Moon was one of three men used by designer James Earle Fraser as inspiration for the Native American face on the Buffalo Nickel.</string>
    <string _locid="120193">Chief Crazy Horse has left Chayton to bring the Cheyenne chiefs to the War Council. He and his riders are circling around Custer's flanks and will arrive later. Be prepared. Build up and defend the Lakota against Custer's subordinates Major Reno and Captain Benteen.\n \nHistory:\n \nCourageous. Wise. Steadfast. There are few names in Native American history as revered as Crazy Horse (Tashunkewitko). The exact date of his birth is unclear, probably sometime around 1840. At birth he was given the name Light Hair or Curly Hair.\n \nAccording to Chief Black Elk, a second cousin, Crazy Horse took his adult name after experiencing a vision in which he saw a horse strangely dancing about like a creature of shadow. He believed this vision gave him great power, so much so that he could go into battle and not be injured. And in fact, Crazy Horse survived many, many battles over the years.\n \nAfter defeating Custer at Little Bighorn in June, 1876, Crazy Horse continued to resist U.S. forces. With food running out, Crazy Horse finally surrendered to U.S. troops in May, 1877.  He spent his remaining days on the Red Cloud Agency in Nebraska. On 5 September 1877, he died of a bayonet wound incurred, it is thought, when he resisted being led to the stockade at Fort Robinson.</string>
    <string _locid="120194">It's not just a coincidence that this building with its stores of grain is near a saloon...\n \nHistory:\n \nFor centuries farmers fed their animals – particularly cattle and sheep – by letting them graze on pastureland. As long as both land and grass was plentiful, this practice worked relatively well.  In the nineteenth century, livestock became even more important economically and farmers started looking for ways to increase farming productivity. They began to grow crops specifically for use by the domesticated animals, such as corn, barley, oats, and hay. The invention of the cylindrical storage silo in the 1880s by Franklin Hiram King was a major advance, as it enabled farmers to store these crops cheaply and relatively free of mold.</string>
    <string _locid="120195">This huge fixed artillery piece can be used by whoever controls the emplacement. It has a long range and does a lot of damage. Just the thing to destroy marauding British soldiers and ships.\n \nHistory:\n \nForts have been used in warfare for thousands of years. Some forts included cannon that could be used to keep the fort secure from enemies. Fixed guns didn't guarantee your fort would be secure, however. In 1775, Fort Ticonderoga in New York was captured from the British by a small band of Americans who snuck in the fort through an unlocked gate. The sleeping British were overcome by the American "Green Mountain Boys," and only one shot was fired.\n \nMany forts were abandoned as they became irrelevant; Fort Ticonderoga was abandoned in 1780.</string>
    <string _locid="120208">Able to carry many soldiers, and move quietly across the ice choked Delaware River.\n \nHistory:\n \nBefore airplanes, superhighways, and railroads enabled fast “overnight” shipping to practically anywhere in the world, hard goods were transported either over land via wagon or over water via barges and flatboats. During the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, the cities that emerged across the eastern U.S. conducted commerce with one another using the existing rivers and waterways. As the U.S. population migrated westward in the early nineteenth century, however, the need for better means of transporting goods to and from the new territories increased.\n \nOn 4 July 1817, construction of the Erie Canal system began in Rome, New York. When completed in October 1825, the canal system stretched over 350 miles from end to end, not including the many other feeder canals branching off from the main route. The Erie Canal enabled trade to flourish by boat between the East Coast and the emerging population centers of the upper Midwest.  </string>
    <string _locid="120196">Forts are strong defensive buildings consisting of walls, towers, gates, and buildings within the Fort walls. Towers fire, so it is wise to attack forts with units that outrange the towers or that do a lot of siege damage. Artillery like Falconets and especially Mortars are good at destroying Forts.\n \nForts can only be built by Fort Wagons, which are sent from the Home City. You may have to unlock the ability to send them. Some civilizations have the ability to send more than one Fort Wagon.\n \nHistory:\n \nForts in the New World ranged from wooden palisades assembled hastily as outposts or for the protection of watersheds to sprawling star forts whose distinctively angled earthen and stone walls protected key ports, mines, cities, and overland trade routes.\n \nFort McHenry, once called Fort Whetstone, was a star fort surrounded on three sides by water. In 1814, it survived a 25-hour bombardment by the British. Francis Scott Key wrote a poem about his experiences during and after the battle, and the story of Fort McHenry and its star-spangled banner became the national anthem of the United States in 1931.</string>
    <string _locid="120197">Holme's bandits are using this Supply Wagon to smuggle Coin into the Black Hills. Catch it and you can take the resources!\n \nHistory:\n \nNapoleon is said to have uttered the following axiom of war: “An army travels on its stomach.”  Wars can be won and lost based on how well an army can maintain its supply lines. One of the first tactics in any conflict is to cut off an opponent’s supply lines. During the eighteenth century, supplies included not only food and ammunition, but other items such as coffee, tobacco, and even rum (for U.S. Colonial soldiers in 1785 were provided 4 ounces of rum per day).\n \nThe Battle of Glorieta, at the Glorieta Pass in New Mexico, illustrates the importance of protecting your supply lines. Also known as the Gettysburg of the West, the Battle of Glorieta pitted Confederate soldiers out of Texas against Union forces from New Mexico. In terms of casualties, the three-day battle was pretty much a toss-up, with both sides experiencing about 50 killed and 60 wounded.\n \nThe key to repelling the Confederate forces in their westward advance was the attack by Union troops on the relatively unguarded Confederate supply wagon train at Canoncito. The entire 80 wagon train and all its supplies of ammo, food, and medicines were burnt and destroyed. Without their supplies, the Confederates were forced to return to Texas, effectively ending their goal of conquering the Southwest.</string>
    <string _locid="120198">Holme's bandits are using this Supply Wagon to smuggle Food into the Black Hills. Catch it and you can take the resources!\n \nHistory:\n \nNapoleon is said to have uttered the following axiom of war: “An army travels on its stomach.”  Wars can be won and lost based on how well an army can maintain its supply lines. One of the first tactics in any conflict is to cut off an opponent’s supply lines. During the eighteenth century, supplies included not only food and ammunition, but other items such as coffee, tobacco, and even rum (for U.S. Colonial soldiers in 1785 were provided 4 ounces of rum per day).\n \nThe Battle of Glorieta, at the Glorieta Pass in New Mexico, illustrates the importance of protecting your supply lines. Also known as the Gettysburg of the West, the Battle of Glorieta pitted Confederate soldiers out of Texas against Union forces from New Mexico. In terms of casualties, the three-day battle was pretty much a toss-up, with both sides experiencing about 50 killed and 60 wounded.\n \nThe key to repelling the Confederate forces in their westward advance was the attack by Union troops on the relatively unguarded Confederate supply wagon train at Canoncito. The entire 80 wagon train and all its supplies of ammo, food, and medicines were burnt and destroyed. Without their supplies, the Confederates were forced to return to Texas, effectively ending their goal of conquering the Southwest.</string>
    <string _locid="120199">Holme's bandits are using this Supply Wagon to smuggle Wood into the Black Hills. Catch it and you can take the resources!\n \nHistory:\n \nNapoleon is said to have uttered the following axiom of war: “An army travels on its stomach.”  Wars can be won and lost based on how well an army can maintain its supply lines. One of the first tactics in any conflict is to cut off an opponent’s supply lines. During the eighteenth century, supplies included not only food and ammunition, but other items such as coffee, tobacco, and even rum (for U.S. Colonial soldiers in 1785 were provided 4 ounces of rum per day).\n \nThe Battle of Glorieta, at the Glorieta Pass in New Mexico, illustrates the importance of protecting your supply lines. Also known as the Gettysburg of the West, the Battle of Glorieta pitted Confederate soldiers out of Texas against Union forces from New Mexico. In terms of casualties, the three-day battle was pretty much a toss-up, with both sides experiencing about 50 killed and 60 wounded.\n \nThe key to repelling the Confederate forces in their westward advance was the attack by Union troops on the relatively unguarded Confederate supply wagon train at Canoncito. The entire 80 wagon train and all its supplies of ammo, food, and medicines were burnt and destroyed. Without their supplies, the Confederates were forced to return to Texas, effectively ending their goal of conquering the Southwest.</string>
    <string _locid="120200">Gold miners gather here while they are working. Be sure to protect them from attacks.\n \nHistory:\n \nDuring the gold rush of 1849, the hills, riverbanks, and streams of California were practically overrun with fortune-seeking newcomers. As the early arrivals panned for gold in the waters’ gravel beds, they soon discovered doing this by hand was painfully tedious and time-consuming. Other methods for extracting the gold from the gravel were developed, including using larger containers called “cradles,” and even high-pressure hydraulic hoses. Other miners chose to dig the gold out from the ore-bearing rock directly, a method that came to be known as “hard-rock mining.”</string>
    <string _locid="120201">Nathaniel attacks with a rifle and tomahawk. He has a lot of hitpoints and two special ranged attacks, Hawkeye Attack and Eagle Eye, that he can use once every couple of minutes. If he falls in a fight, he collapses and has to regenerate enough health to be recovered by allies. Nathaniel can collect Treasures and build Trading Posts near Native settlements and Trade Routes.\n \nHistory:\n \nThe son of John Black, Nathaniel was raised by his Haudenosaunee mother Nonahkee and uncle Ká:nien. Prior to the American Revolution, Nathaniel helped unite several Haudenosaunee villages into a cooperative of shared interests and economy. Nathaniel isn’t given to many words. He’s a man of action. When he speaks, he speaks his heart plain and direct. And when he acts, anyone who stands in his way should beware.</string>
    <string _locid="120202">This is a Falconet from Washington's Cannonworks.\n \nHistory:\n \nFalconets were among the smallest artillery. They weighed about 280 pounds, had a six-foot barrel and used about a pound of powder to fire a one-pound shot. Still, the small quantity of powder (relative to larger artillery pieces) was enough to make a properly braced Falconet fly back up to 10 yards when fired.</string>
    <string _locid="120203">This is a Heavy Cannon from Washington's Cannonworks.\n \nHistory:\n \nThe logistics of moving, maintaining, positioning, aiming, and firing artillery required a highly drilled and disciplined team with a sharp commander. In addition to the men and artillery pieces in his command, an artillery officer had to see to the horses used to haul the pieces around - sometimes up to six for heavier guns. When one side in a battle could field hundreds of artillery pieces, the logistics of just moving them into position were taxing. "Heavy Cannon" is a relative term, but in general, cannon considered 'heavy' were typically used as permanent gun emplacements to defend Forts and strategic locations.</string>
    <string _locid="120204">This is a Mortar from Washington's Cannonworks.\n \nHistory:\n \nA mortar is an artillery piece with a short barrel and a large bore that fires massive projectiles in a high arc. The name "mortar" probably refers to its resemblance to the mortar of a mortar and pestle. The high arc of a mortar's fire reaches emplacements and buildings that are screened by terrain or walls or other permanent defenses. The projectile a mortar fired was filled with gunpowder and fitted with a fuse that was lit right before firing the mortar. The artillery crew had to carefully measure how long to make the fuse for the mortar to explode at the right moment (usually on impact). This made mortars much better at firing on buildings and fortifications than on fluid groups of moving troops.</string>
    <string _locid="120205">This is a Rocket from Washington's Cannonworks.\n \nHistory:\n \nThe first rockets used in warfare were developed by the Chinese and Indians. The principle is similar to a bottle rocket, where explosive propellant (gunpowder) propels a missile (the rocket) and is stabilized by a stick that extends well beyond the body of the rocket. It was William Congreve, a British officer, who developed their use for warfare in the Napoleonic era. His rockets were tubes capped by cones and filled with gunpowder and either shrapnel or shot. They were fired from structures that consisted of a ladder with supports for the body of the rocket and a frame to prop up both ladder and rocket. These were tall affairs, and needed to be, when the stick of a large rocket could be as long as 15 feet! The "rockets' red glare" in the Star-Spangled Banner, the national anthem of the US, refers to the rockets used by the British navy in their assault on Fort McHenry in 1814.</string>
    <string _locid="120206">Stop reading this and save the railroad worker!\n \nHistory:\n \nIn the mid-nineteenth century, the discovery of gold in California and the need for efficient postal routes led to interest in building a transcontinental railroad across North America. Initially, a shortage of workers made construction of the railroad difficult. Soon veterans of the Civil War swelled the ranks of the workers and allowed the Union Pacific Corporation to complete its railroad across over 1,700 miles of wilderness in less than four years. The railroad workers faced low wages and difficult working conditions; labor strikes were common. Union Pacific broke the strikes by bringing in Chinese workers to complete the railroad.</string>
    <string _locid="120207">This sturdy earthwork will repel most attacks.\n \nHistory:\n \nWhere there was a need to fortify positions against other Europeans with artillery, sophisticated and expensive Redoubt forts were built. These were relatively low and sloped to reduce artillery effectiveness, and built of stone if possible. Trenches, dry moats, bastions (firing points extending out from the fort), and interlocking fields of fire slowed the advance of enemy soldiers within the range of cannon and musket fire. Examples of Redoubt forts of the era include Fort Ticonderoga near Lake Champlain, New York, and Fort Louisbourg in Nova Scotia.</string>
    <string _locid="120209">This ramshackle shelter was not built by a master carpenter (or even a poor carpenter), but it will keep the wind and snow off of the soldiers who built it. Now if only they could find something to eat...\n \nHistory:\n \nGeorge Washington placed the Continental Army in winter quarters at Valley Forge December 19, 1777, reasonably close to the British army wintering in Philadelphia. The winter months were a severe ordeal for Washington’s army, and the fate of the revolution hung in the balance. They sheltered in temporary wooden huts built partly underground, subsisting on the meager supplies that reached them. The army survived the winter, however, and by the summer of 1778 had been remade as a fighting force.</string>
    <string _locid="120210">This tattered Colonial soldier and his buddies have to make do for themselves this winter. Until he and the other soldiers collect enough Wood to build shelters against the cold, they will all be vulnerable to the elements. After the shelters comes Food. And after Food, the British. Poor guys. It's going to be a long winter. Can Nathaniel and General Washington see them safely through it?\n \nHistory:\n \nThe army that Washington led to Valley Forge in 1777 was a rag-tag group of citizen militia that had seen little success against the trained professional soldiers of the British army. After an arduous winter the supply situation improved by early spring and training commenced. With the help of European volunteer instructors, the frozen and starving citizen-soldiers of January were turned into an effective fighting army by June, 1778.</string>
    <string _locid="120211">This wagon is carrying food to the soldiers at Valley Forge. Make sure it gets there!\n \nHistory:\n \nNapoleon is said to have uttered the following axiom of war: “An army travels on its stomach.”  Wars can be won and lost based on how well an army can maintain its supply lines. One of the first tactics in any conflict is to cut off an opponent’s supply lines. During the eighteenth century, supplies included not only food and ammunition, but other items such as coffee, tobacco, and even rum (for U.S. Colonial soldiers in 1785 were provided 4 ounces of rum per day).\n \nThe Battle of Glorieta, at the Glorieta Pass in New Mexico, illustrates the importance of protecting your supply lines. Also known as the Gettysburg of the West, the Battle of Glorieta pitted Confederate soldiers out of Texas against Union forces from New Mexico. In terms of casualties, the three-day battle was pretty much a toss-up, with both sides experiencing about 50 killed and 60 wounded.\n \nThe key to repelling the Confederate forces in their westward advance was the attack by Union troops on the relatively unguarded Confederate supply wagon train at Canoncito. The entire 80 wagon train and all its supplies of ammo, food, and medicines were burnt and destroyed. Without their supplies, the Confederates were forced to return to Texas, effectively ending their goal of conquering the Southwest.</string>
    <string _locid="120212">Forts are strong defensive buildings consisting of walls, towers, gates, and buildings within the fort walls. Towers fire, so it is wise to attack forts with units that outrange the towers or that do a lot of building damage. Artillery like Falconets and especially Mortars are good at destroying forts.\n \nHistory:\n \nThe earliest setters in North America built wooden forts around or near their settlements for protection. Trees were abundant and log palisades could be built quickly. An adequately manned wooden fort was difficult to attack successfully without artillery. As the Europeans moved into and across the continent, wooden forts went up at settlements on the expanding frontier. The modern names of some frontier settlements no longer reflect their original designation as a fort (Fort Duquesne is now Pittsburgh) while others retained their original name (Fort Wayne, Indiana, and Fort Smith, Arkansas).</string>
    <string _locid="120214">A group of special improvements unique to the Native American civilizations. These Native Bonuses will be available in some native buildings and appear as larger buttons in the command panel.</string>
    <string _locid="120215">A way for Native American civilizations to get a variety of bonuses. You can select any of the Ceremonies in the Community Plaza to achieve a specific bonus. As you gain wisdom from the Tribal Elders and move through the Ages, new Ceremonies will become available for you to choose from. There are two Ceremonies that are made available only via Tribal Council shipments. Only one Ceremony can be performed at a time.</string>
    <string _locid="120216">An alternate 5th Age for European civilizations. If you are playing a European civilization and have reached the 4th age, you have the option to either revolt or try to go to the 5th, Imperial Age. If you revolt, you must choose between revolutionary nations, each offering a different bonus. When the revolution is activated, your flag is changed to a new one and your settlers transform into Revolutionaries. Revolutionaries are not settlers - they cannot gather or construct buildings, but are effective in combat.\n\nOnce you have revolted you can not produce fishing boats or villagers, but most revolutionary home cities provide a card to lift this ban. Each revolutionary home city comes with its own unique cards and often offers repeatable shipments for: more Revolutionaries, Gatling Guns, Ironclads, or Fort Wagons.</string>
    <string _locid="120217">An ability that some units can use to make themselves mostly invisible. When Stealth is activated, the unit fades out and becomes invisible to an opponent. His speed is also greatly lessened. A unit cannot “go Stealthy” if it is in the line of sight of an enemy. Certain units, namely War Chiefs, Explorers, Spies, and Town Centers, can see Stealthy units. Stealthy units include: Navajo Riflemen, Spies, Ninja, Tashunke Prowlers, Forest Prowlers, and Jaguar Prowl Knights.</string>
    <string _locid="120218">An alternate to victory by military conquest. If you are playing a Standard game, and your team owns more than half the trading post sites in the game (both native settlements and trade routes count), then you can activate the Trade Monopoly button.  This starts a timer, and prevents your team from building any more Trading Posts until the timer has ended. The other team has until the timer’s end to destroy enough of your team’s Trading Posts to bring the total down to 50% or fewer of the sites available. For example, on a map with 7 trading posts, if you started a Trade Monopoly victory count-down while owning 5 of the posts, your enemy would have to destroy 2 posts to stop the timer.</string>
    <string _locid="120219">A game type that enforces a ban on fighting until a pre-determined amount of time has passed. When starting a game, you can select the Treaty option. A Treaty game starts with a period of non-combat: 10-40 minutes, depending on what your choice. During this time, you can engage in combat only vs. treasure guardians. You can only construct buildings within a certain radius of your starting town center. Your combat buildings (town center, outposts, etc.) can still shoot at intruders, to prevent an enemy from exploiting the peaceful early part of the game by stationing his troops inconveniently inside your homeland.\n \nTrade Monopoly and Revolution options are disabled in Treaty games.</string>
    <string _locid="120220">A land-based unit that can collect Treasures and often has special abilities that affect units nearby. The War Chief is a mighty unit available to Native American civilizations at game start. Each native tribe has its own unique War Chief, with his own special improvements (check out the Community Plaza’s Big Button!), tribal council shipments, and powers.</string>
    <string _locid="120221">This Chest of Coin provides Coin at a very fast rate, but in a very limited amount. Use a gatherer to collect the Coin. Chests usually come from the Home City or Tribal Council to Town Centers or other buildings. They provide resources very quickly, but in a very limited amount. Any player can gather from any crate, which means allies can share them or enemies can steal them if they are left unattended at a Town Center. Guard crates carefully, or better yet, use them as soon as possible!\n \nHistory:\n \nSupplies from Europe were often vital to the survival of a struggling colony in the New World. The colony at Roanoke had the misfortune of being established during a time of drought in the area, leading to difficulties growing Food. In addition, the colony's relationship with the Native American people in the area was not good. The colonists had so many difficulties that they left the colony before a desperately needed supply ship could arrive.\n \nWhen the supply ship finally arrived, it found the colony abandoned. Fifteen men from the ship decided to stay behind while the ship returned to England. When another ship made the crossing to rescue the men left behind, they found no sign of them except for the bones of one man. No one knows for certain what happened to the others.</string>
    <string _locid="120222">This large Chest of Coin provides Coin at a very fast rate, but in a very limited amount. Use a gatherer to collect the Coin. Chests usually come from the Home City or Tribal Council to Town Centers or other buildings. They provide resources very quickly, but in a very limited amount. Any player can gather from any crate, which means allies can share them or enemies can steal them if they are left unattended at a Town Center. Guard crates carefully, or better yet, use them as soon as possible!\n \nHistory:\n \nSupplies from Europe were often vital to the survival of a struggling colony in the New World. The colony at Roanoke had the misfortune of being established during a time of drought in the area, leading to difficulties growing Food. In addition, the colony's relationship with the Native American people in the area was not good. The colonists had so many difficulties that they left the colony before a desperately needed supply ship could arrive.\n \nWhen the supply ship finally arrived, it found the colony abandoned. Fifteen men from the ship decided to stay behind while the ship returned to England. When another ship made the crossing to rescue the men left behind, they found no sign of them except for the bones of one man. No one knows for certain what happened to the others.</string>
    <string _locid="120223">This Crate of Food provides Food at a very fast rate, but in a very limited amount. Use a gatherer to collect the Food. Crates usually come from the Home City or Tribal Council to Town Centers or other buildings. They provide resources very quickly, but in a very limited amount. Any player can gather from any crate, which means allies can share them or enemies can steal them if they are left unattended at a Town Center. Guard crates carefully, or better yet, use them as soon as possible!\n \nHistory:\n \nSupplies from Europe were often vital to the survival of a struggling colony in the New World. The colony at Roanoke had the misfortune of being established during a time of drought in the area, leading to difficulties with growing Food. In addition, the colony's relationship with the Native American people in the area was not good. The colonists had so many difficulties that they left the colony before a desperately needed supply ship could arrive.\n \nWhen the supply ship finally arrived, it found the colony abandoned. Fifteen men from the ship decided to stay behind while the ship returned to England. When another ship made the crossing to rescue the men left behind, they found no sign of them except for the bones of one man. No one knows for certain what happened to the others.</string>
    <string _locid="120224">This large Crate of Food provides Food at a very fast rate, but in a very limited amount. Use a gatherer to collect the Food. Crates usually come from the Home City or Tribal Council to Town Centers or other buildings. They provide resources very quickly, but in a very limited amount. Any player can gather from any crate, which means allies can share them or enemies can steal them if they are left unattended at a Town Center. Guard crates carefully, or better yet, use them as soon as possible!\n \nHistory:\n \nSupplies from Europe were often vital to the survival of a struggling colony in the New World. The colony at Roanoke had the misfortune of being established during a time of drought in the area, leading to difficulties growing Food. In addition, the colony's relationship with the Native American people in the area was not good. The colonists had so many difficulties that they left the colony before a desperately needed supply ship could arrive.\n \nWhen the supply ship finally arrived, it found the colony abandoned. Fifteen men from the ship decided to stay behind while the ship returned to England. When another ship made the crossing to rescue the men left behind, they found no sign of them except for the bones of one man. No one knows for certain what happened to the others.</string>
    <string _locid="120225">This Cord of Wood provides Wood at a very fast rate, but in a very limited amount. Use a gatherer to collect the Wood. Cords usually come from the Home City or Tribal Council to Town Centers or other buildings. They provide resources very quickly, but in a very limited amount. Any player can gather from any crate, which means allies can share them or enemies can steal them if they are left unattended at a Town Center. Guard crates carefully, or better yet, use them as soon as possible!\n \nHistory:\n \nSupplies from Europe were often vital to the survival of a struggling colony in the New World. The colony at Roanoke had the misfortune of being established during a time of drought in the area, leading to difficulties growing Food. In addition, the colony's relationship with the Native American people in the area was not good. The colonists had so many difficulties that they left the colony before a desperately needed supply ship could arrive.\n \nWhen the supply ship finally arrived, it found the colony abandoned. Fifteen men from the ship decided to stay behind while the ship returned to England. When another ship made the crossing to rescue the men left behind, they found no sign of them except for the bones of one man. No one knows for certain what happened to the others.</string>
    <string _locid="120226">This large Cord of Wood provides Wood at a very fast rate, but in a very limited amount. Use a gatherer to collect the Wood. Cords usually come from the Home City or Tribal Council to Town Centers or other buildings. They provide resources very quickly, but in a very limited amount. Any player can gather from any crate, which means allies can share them or enemies can steal them if they are left unattended at a Town Center. Guard crates carefully, or better yet, use them as soon as possible!\n \nHistory:\n \nSupplies from Europe were often vital to the survival of a struggling colony in the New World. The colony at Roanoke had the misfortune of being established during a time of drought in the area, leading to difficulties growing Food. In addition, the colony's relationship with the Native American people in the area was not good. The colonists had so many difficulties that they left the colony before a desperately needed supply ship could arrive.\n \nWhen the supply ship finally arrived, it found the colony abandoned. Fifteen men from the ship decided to stay behind while the ship returned to England. When another ship made the crossing to rescue the men left behind, they found no sign of them except for the bones of one man. No one knows for certain what happened to the others.</string>
    <string _locid="120227">The Healer is a unit that heals other units. He has a poor attack, but may heal other units at a short range.\n \nUnits do not regenerate their health on their own, so a Healer can prolong the life of your armies significantly.\n \nHistory:\n \nBoth "Healer" and "Elder" refer to Native American healers and spiritual leaders. Not all were male and many of their responsibilities had little to do with physical healing. They were responsible for both the physical and the spiritual health of the people in their nation.</string>
    <string _locid="120228">This animal is likely to have been tamed by a War Chief (or captured by an Explorer) and is now a Pet. Pets are good at scouting and accompanying Explorers and War Chiefs as they search the map for resources and Treasures. Pets can also be effective at raiding enemy camps, killing Settlers and Villagers handily, but should run from military units unless they have overwhelming numbers.\n \nHistory:\n \nScientific Name: Ursus americanus\nApprox. Size: 130 lb. (female); 380 lb. (male)\nDiet: Fruits, grasses, roots, nuts, herbs, insects, fish, carrion\n \nThe black bear is the most common bear in North America. They live in a variety of habitats, preferring forests with an abundance of undergrowth that provides them with food, shelter, and protection from their rare, but fearsome, predators. Black bears scale trees to escape threats. Humans and other bears, even other black bears, are the chief predator of black bears.\n \nIn colder climates, the black bear enters true hibernation, but in warmer ranges the bears do not reach the depth of hibernating sleep, though they sleep for extended periods of time in the cold months.\n \nThere are sixteen subspecies of black bear. One, the Ursus americanus kermodei, is a white, but not albino, subspecies that lives in the Pacific Northwest and is referred to as a Spirit Bear in some native traditions. Ursus americanus emmonsii, the glacier bear, has gray and white hairs in its coat, giving a striking blue appearance to this bear's coat.</string>
    <string _locid="120229">This animal is likely to have been tamed by a War Chief (or captured by an Explorer) and is now a Pet. Pets are good at scouting and accompanying Explorers and War Chiefs as they search the map for resources and Treasures. Pets can also be effective at raiding enemy camps, killing Settlers and Villagers handily, but should run from military units unless they have overwhelming numbers.\n \nHistory:\n \nScientific Name: Felis concolor\nApprox. Size: 7 ft. long, 170 lb.\nDiet: Large and small mammals\n \nAlso commonly called mountain lion, puma, and panther, the cougar has a tawny red or gray coat and pale belly. Before European settlement of the New World, cougars and their relatives ranged the length and breadth of North and South America, and though their territory is much smaller now, they have one of the largest ranges of any animal in the New World. They chiefly hunt large mammals, but will eat smaller game if need be.</string>
    <string _locid="120230">This animal is likely to have been tamed by a War Chief (or captured by an Explorer) and is now a Pet. Pets are good at scouting and accompanying Explorers and War Chiefs as they search the map for resources and Treasures. Pets can also be effective at raiding enemy camps, killing Settlers and Villagers handily, but should run from military units unless they have overwhelming numbers.\n \nHistory:\n \nScientific Name: Canis latrans\nApprox. Size: 20 in. at the shoulder, 30 lb.\nDiet: Small and large mammals, carrion, garbage\n \nA small, grayish brown wolflike canine that inhabits deserts, prairies, and other grasslands, but can survive close proximity with humans. Clearing of forest land in some areas has actually expanded the range of coyotes in some areas and, because they are smart and adaptable, they are learning how to live alongside humans. They communicate with long, wavering howls and sharp yips that individuals vocalize on top of one another. This can make and eerie cacophony, haunting and beautiful in its own way.</string>
    <string _locid="120231">This animal is likely to have been tamed by a War Chief (or captured by an Explorer) and is now a Pet. Pets are good at scouting and accompanying Explorers and War Chiefs as they search the map for resources and Treasures. Pets can also be effective at raiding enemy camps, killing Settlers and Villagers handily, but should run from military units unless they have overwhelming numbers.\n \nHistory:\n \nScientific Name: Ursus arctos subsp. horribilis\nApprox. Size: 500 lb. (female); 900 lb. (male)\nDiet: Roots, fungi, fish, insects, large and small mammals\n \nA subspecies of the largest species of bear (the brown bear), grizzlies get their name from the white tips of their fur that give them a rough, weathered appearance. The hump of muscle, visible in profile, between the grizzly's shoulders is massive and gives incredible strength to their forequarters, allowing them to dig and strike. Its claws three to four inches long; there are not many mammals that can withstand the powerful strike of a grizzly bear. They spend the better part of the fall season fattening up for the lean winter months, when they become sluggish if not actually hibernating. Grizzlies find or excavate dens for the winter months, usually just large enough for themselves, with an entry that lets air circulate.\n \nGrizzly bears once ranged throughout North America west of the Mississippi and as far south as Mexico. Today they live in rugged, remote mountain and forest wilderness areas.</string>
    <string _locid="120232">This animal is likely to have been tamed by a War Chief (or captured by an Explorer) and is now a Pet. Pets are good at scouting and accompanying Explorers and War Chiefs as they search the map for resources and Treasures. Pets can also be effective at raiding enemy camps, killing Settlers and Villagers handily, but should run from military units unless they have overwhelming numbers.\n \nHistory:\n \nScientific Name: Panthera onca\nApprox. Size: Up to 7 ft. long, 200 lb.\nDiet: Deer, cattle, peccary, capybara, monkeys, fish\n \nJaguars are often confused with leopards, another tawny, spotted cat. A distinguishing feature of the jaguar is that its spots have small black dots or irregular shapes within rosette patterns. Jaguars are also stockier and have larger heads than leopards. Both jaguars and leopards have melanistic, or black, variants. Without spots, black jaguars can be differentiated from black leopards primarily by their stocky build. Both big cats, whether jaguars or leopards, black or spotted, are commonly, if mistakenly, called panthers.\n \nHistorically, jaguars ranged from the southern parts of North America down to the southern most tip of South America, but their ranges now are in central and northern South America. Jaguars enjoy a rare, unchallenged perch at the top of the wild food chain. In their South American habitat, they have no predators and few real competitors, apart from humans.</string>
    <string _locid="120233">This animal is likely to have been tamed by a War Chief (or captured by an Explorer) and is now a Pet. Pets are good at scouting and accompanying Explorers and War Chiefs as they search the map for resources and Treasures. Pets can also be effective at raiding enemy camps, killing Settlers and Villagers handily, but should run from military units unless they have overwhelming numbers.\n \nHistory:\n \nScientific Name: Ursus Maritimus\nApprox. Size: Up to 600 lb. (female); up to 1,700 lb. (male)\nDiet: Seals, whales, caribou\n \nPolar bears live further north than any other land mammal and are the largest living land carnivores. Polar bears use a variety of hunting techniques. White fur and padded paws mean they can stalk seals resting on the ice. They have been known to wait next to seal breathing holes for hours in order to pull a 250-pound seal up onto the ice. They are also strong enough to create new breathing holes to bait seals.\n \nDespite their hunting strategies, polar bears make successful kills less than 15% of the time. Fortunately, they can eat a lot of meat, over 150 pounds at one sitting, and can go without food for weeks. Scores of polar bears have been seen feeding on the carcasses of dead whales.</string>
    <string _locid="120234">This animal is likely to have been tamed by a War Chief (or captured by an Explorer) and is now a Pet. Pets are good at scouting and accompanying Explorers and War Chiefs as they search the map for resources and Treasures. Pets can also be effective at raiding enemy camps, killing Settlers and Villagers handily, but should run from military units unless they have overwhelming numbers.\n \nHistory:\n \nScientific Name: Canis lupus\nApprox. Size: 50-150 lb.\nDiet: Deer, caribou, elk, sheep, small mammals\n \nHistorically, gray wolves could be found throughout the Northern Hemisphere, from the Arctic to the tropics. Habitat destruction and hunting have greatly reduced their range. They are highly social animals that live and hunt in packs of up to thirty-six individuals led by an alpha male and female. Unrelated immigrants may be adopted into a pack. Packs are generally territorial and patrol their domains against intruders. Except for the red wolf, all living wolves are considered to be part of the C. lupus species. Domestic dogs, including feral subspecies such as dingos, are also classified as wolves. Domestication, perhaps as many as five different times, has lead to significant (but genetically irrelevant) differences between wolves and dogs.</string>
    <string _locid="120235">This tree can be chopped down for Wood by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.\n \nHistory:\n \nThe wetlands of the bayou are host to many species of plants and trees, including fragrant, glossy-leaved magnolias and spreading oaks shrouded with gray-green Spanish moss. In the deep backwaters of the bayou, grasses and sedges grow thick in the underbrush. In some areas, winter flooding carries away a lot of leaf litter, making the ground relatively uncluttered, except for new growth and grasses.</string>
    <string _locid="120236">This tree can be chopped down for Wood by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.\n \nHistory:\n \nLong and shortleaf pine, redbud, several species of birch, maple, and oak, and many other trees form the woodlands of the Carolinas. Coastal areas of South Carolina are noted for banana trees and palmettos, the latter gives South Carolina its nickname, "The Palmetto State."</string>
    <string _locid="120237">This tree can be chopped down for Wood by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.\n \nHistory:\n \nWhite eastern pine, white oak, sugar maple, and red pine are some of the trees that live in the land surrounding the Great Lakes. The British used white pines as masts on tall ships. The French were the first Europeans to make use of the tall, straight trees for forts and fortifications in their early explorations into the wilderness around the Great Lakes.</string>
    <string _locid="120238">This tree can be chopped down for Wood by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.\n \nHistory:\n \nPlant species in Patagonia, the southernmost tip of South America, vary from grasses and small, hardy shrubs on the plains to evergreen pines and hardwoods on the mountainous slopes of the Andes. The southern birch is commonly found growing, stunted and bent, on the windy plains.</string>
    <string _locid="120239">This tree can be chopped down for Wood by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.\n \nHistory:\n \nTrees vary widely across the entire range of the Rocky Mountains and include juniper, oak, willow, fir, spruce, and pine. Ponderosa pine with its peculiar "puzzle bark" grows on southern slopes at relatively low elevations. Trees like the Engelmann spruce grow at about 9,000 feet, and the gnarled limber pine grows up to the treeline, sometimes hunkering in the shelter of rocks. Above the tree line there are arctic temperatures and very strong winds. The low, scrubby tundra plants that survive here are specially adapted to trap as much heat as possible and shield themselves from wind and ultraviolet radiation.</string>
    <string _locid="120240">This tree can be chopped down for Wood by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.\n \nHistory:\n \nTexas is the second largest state behind Alaska. There are many regions and climates, ranging from pine forests and bayous to grassy plains and deserts. Common trees are juniper, mesquite, pecan, and a number of oaks. Central and northern Texas is the southern edge of the Great Plains and has wide grassy prairies. There are stands of pine in the east and scrubby juniper and mesquite in the drier west.</string>
    <string _locid="120241">This tree can be chopped down for Wood by gatherers - Settlers, Villagers, Coureurs des Bois, Settler Wagons, and Cree Coureurs.\n \nHistory:\n \nThe Yukon has long winters and short summers, when hardy grains and flowering plants thrive briefly. The sparsely limbed subalpine fir is well adapted to the heavy snows of Yukon winter. Forests of black spruce and white spruce grow throughout the region, cropping up amidst sedgewort-covered plains.</string>
    <string _locid="120242">The Pirate is a mercenary infantry unit available only from the Saloon. He has a good melee attack, but no range. Because he does his damage in melee combat, the Pirate is vulnerable to ranged attacks while he gets close to his enemies. Keep this in mind when commanding this and any other melee infantry units.</string>
    <string _locid="120243">Chayton attacks with a rifle and saber. He has a lot of hitpoints and two special ranged attacks, Hawkeye Attack and Eagle Eye, that he can use once every couple of minutes. If he falls in a fight, he collapses and has to regenerate enough health to be recovered by allies. Chayton can collect Treasures and build Trading Posts near Native settlements and Trade Routes.\n \nHistory:\n \nNathaniel's half-Lakota grandson, Chayton Black, seems to have inherited his family's tendency to wind up smack dab in the middle of opposing forces. When gold is discovered in the Black Hills, tensions between the Lakota Nation and settlers erupt. Against a backdrop of greed, fear, and prejudice, Chayton discovers that taking the convenient side can cost everything - even his own identity.</string>
    <string _locid="120244">The most densely populated region of the New World in 1492 was Mesoamerica, where North and Central America meet in modern Mexico and the Yucatan Peninsula. The people living here were called the Aztecs (also Mexica or Tenochca); they built an amazing civilization centered on their great capital city of Tenochtitlan (modern Mexico City). This was one of the largest cities in the world (with an estimated population of 200,000), and arguably more beautiful and cleaner than any contemporary capital in Europe.\n \nThe Aztecs were just one of several tribes in the area, but had risen to prominence due to their ferocity in battle and adept diplomacy. Their soldiers wielded weapons of wood and stone, and they often sought prisoners to be sacrificed in religious ceremonies. Their society depended on sophisticated agricultural techniques; from them the world learned of foodstuffs including tomatoes, corn, cocoa, and chili peppers. They were handicapped by the lack of large domesticated animals (they had no horse or ox), and the use of the wheel only in toys. Everything to be moved was carried by human porters.\n \nDespite their large population and fighting prowess, the Aztecs fell relatively quickly to the determined Spanish conquistadores under Cortez. This was due in large part to the epidemics the Europeans brought ashore. By some estimates the Aztec population of 12 million people in 1520 had fallen to one million by 1600. The Spanish also allied with the Aztecs' enemies to increase the size of their armies, and had the advantages of steel and gunpowder weapons.</string>
    <string _locid="120245">The late sixteenth century confederation of five (later six) tribes into the Haudenosaunee League in upstate New York created the most dominant native force in the northeast United States and eastern Canada. At the height of their empire in the late seventeenth century, they held sway over lands stretching from the Chesapeake Bay to the Mississippi and Illinois Rivers, and from Kentucky to Ontario. They are remarkable for many achievements, including their political system of checks and balances. The central law of its confederacy was to never war with each other. Against enemies, however, they usually presented a united political and military front .\n \nThe Haudenosaunee population had boomed following the adoption of agriculture in the fourteenth century, and they settled in villages of distinctive wood-framed and bark-covered longhouses. The first Europeans they encountered were the French, fighting against them in support of other tribes along the St. Lawrence. The Haudenosaunee in turn traded for weapons with the Dutch of New Amsterdam. A series of wars followed, mostly over the fur trade. The Haudenosaunee were often in the middle when France and Britain engaged in their periodic wars.\n \nBy the later eighteenth century the Haudenosaunee were being pressured by English settlers moving west from the coast and down the Ohio River Valley. When the American Revolution broke out in 1776, the Haudenosaunee tried to remain neutral, but the league finally splintered and tribes fought on both sides. In 1779 George Washington sent three columns into Haudenosaunee territory, burning forty villages, and driving most of them into Canada. The millions of acres the Haudenosaunee once held in New York were reduced to a few small reservations, which they still hold today.</string>
    <string _locid="120246">The Healer is a unit that heals other units. He has a poor attack, but may heal other units at a short range.\n \nUnits do not regenerate their health on their own, so a Healer can prolong the life of your armies significantly.</string>
    <string _locid="120247">Both "Healer" and "Elder" refer to Native American healers and spiritual leaders. Not all were male and many of their responsibilities had little to do with physical healing. They were responsible for both the physical and the spiritual health of the people in their nation.</string>
    <string _locid="120248">The term militia refers to a citizen's military force, and not under the direct control or authority of a central government. Each of the original thirteen British colonies in North America had their own militias. They were composed of volunteers from a variety of backgrounds. During the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, it was considered one's civic duty to serve in the local militia to protect the colony from outside attacks.\n \nDuring the early days of the U.S. Revolutionary War, local militias played a key role in the initial skirmishes with British regulars. The battles of Lexington and Bunker Hill were carried out by local militias. To bolster the fledgling country's military capabilities, the Continental Congress established a formal American Continental Army on 14 June 1775, which officially created six companies of expert riflemen, from Pennsylvania, Maryland, and Virginia.</string>
    <string _locid="121053">Aztecs (Mexica)</string>
    <string _locid="121054">Haudenosaunee</string>
    <string _locid="121000">Lakota</string>
    <string _locid="121001">Apache (Ndee/Nnee)</string>
    <string _locid="121002">Cheyenne (Tsitsistas)</string>
    <string _locid="121003">Huron (Wyandot)</string>
    <string _locid="121004">Klamath (Maklak)</string>
    <string _locid="121005">Mapuche</string>
    <string _locid="121006">Navajo (Diné)</string>
    <string _locid="121007">Zapotec (Ben 'Zaa)</string>
    <string _locid="121008">Cuauhtemoc</string>
    <string _locid="121009">Hiawatha</string>
    <string _locid="121010">Gall</string>
    <string _locid="121011">Ram</string>
    <string _locid="121012">Rifle Rider</string>
    <string _locid="121013">Aztec War Chief</string>
    <string _locid="121014">Haudenosaunee War Chief</string>
    <string _locid="121015">Lakota War Chief</string>
    <string _locid="121016">Travois, Builder</string>
    <string _locid="121017">Travois, Trade</string>
    <string _locid="121055">Healer</string>
    <string _locid="121018">Aztec House</string>
    <string _locid="121019">Andes</string>
    <string _locid="121020">Araucania</string>
    <string _locid="121021">California</string>
    <string _locid="121022">Hispaniola</string>
    <string _locid="121023">Northwest Territory</string>
    <string _locid="121024">Orinoco</string>
    <string _locid="121025">Painted Desert</string>
    <string _locid="121026">Unknown</string>
    <string _locid="121027">Crabeater Seal</string>
    <string _locid="121028">Guanaco</string>
    <string _locid="121029">Mine, Copper</string>
    <string _locid="121030">Mine, Tin</string>
    <string _locid="121031">Tree, Andes</string>
    <string _locid="121032">Tree, Araucania</string>
    <string _locid="121033">Tree, California</string>
    <string _locid="121034">Tree, Northwest Territory</string>
    <string _locid="121035">Tree, Painted Desert</string>
    <string _locid="121036">Campaign: Fire and Shadow</string>
    <string _locid="121037">Act I: Fire</string>
    <string _locid="121038">Nathaniel Black</string>
    <string _locid="121039">General George Washington</string>
    <string _locid="121040">Colonel Sven Kuechler</string>
    <string _locid="121041">Act II: Shadow</string>
    <string _locid="121042">Chayton Black</string>
    <string _locid="121043">William Holme</string>
    <string _locid="121044">General George Armstrong Custer</string>
    <string _locid="121045">Campaign: Blood, Ice, Steel</string>
    <string _locid="121046">Native Bonuses</string>
    <string _locid="121047">Ceremony</string>
    <string _locid="121048">Revolution</string>
    <string _locid="121049">Stealth</string>
    <string _locid="121050">Trade Monopoly</string>
    <string _locid="121051">Treaty Mode</string>
    <string _locid="121052">War Chiefs</string>
  </language>
</stringtable>