<objectivestext mission="">
  <objective mission="01" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Left-click Arkantos to select him.</objective>
  <objective mission="01" id="2">OBJECTIVE: With Arkantos selected, right-click near the flag.</objective>
  <objective mission="01" id="3">OBJECTIVE: Drag a box around Arkantos and the other men to select them.</objective>
  <objective mission="01" id="4">OBJECTIVE: With your soldiers selected, right-click near the next flag to keep moving along the trail.</objective>
  <objective mission="01" id="5">OBJECTIVE: Move the mouse to the edge of the screen to scroll the view in the main game window.</objective>
  <objective mission="01" id="6">OBJECTIVE: With your units selected, right-click the army banner to create an army.</objective>
  <objective mission="01" id="7">OBJECTIVE: Seek out and kill the Fenris Wolf.  With your units selected, right-click the wolf to attack.</objective>
  <objective mission="02" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Left-click the settlement.</objective>
  <objective mission="02" id="2">OBJECTIVE: With the settlement selected, left-click the villager button to train a villager.</objective>
  <objective mission="02" id="3">OBJECTIVE: With a villager selected, right-click on a goat to gather food.</objective>
  <objective mission="02" id="4">OBJECTIVE: With a villager selected, right-click on the farm to gather food.</objective>
  <objective mission="02" id="5">OBJECTIVE: Gather 100 gold, 100 food, and 100 wood.  Select villagers, then right-click on resources such as trees, gold mines, and food sources.</objective>
  <objective mission="02" id="6">OBJECTIVE: Select a villager, left-click the temple button, then left-click in the main game window where you want to place the temple.</objective>
  <objective mission="02" id="7">OBJECTIVE: Earn 5 favor.  Select villagers and right-click the shrine to earn favor.</objective>
  <objective mission="02" id="8">OBJECTIVE: Use the Restoration God Power to heal your soldiers.  Click the Restoration button, then left-click anywhere in the main game window.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Advance to the next Age by selecting the settlement and choosing a minor god.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="2">OBJECTIVE: Select a villager, left-click the Academy button, and place it.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="3">OBJECTIVE: Queue up several hoplites by selecting the Academy, then clicking the hoplite button at least four times.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="4">OBJECTIVE: Select a villager, left-click the Sentry Tower, and place it.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="5">OBJECTIVE: Select the Temple, then click the centaur button.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="6">OBJECTIVE: Select a villager, left-click the Town Center button, then left-click the settlement to claim it.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="7">OBJECTIVE: Select the tower, then left-click the watch tower button to upgrade all your towers.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="8">OBJECTIVE: Destroy all three tents at the pirate camp.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="9">OBJECTIVE: Select a villager, left-click the House button, then left-click in the main game window to place the House.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="10">OBJECTIVE: Select the Town Center and ring the town bell to protect your villagers, then wait for the initial pirate attack.</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="11">OBJECTIVE: Select the Town Center, then left-click the flashing button to send your villagers back to work..</objective>
  <objective mission="03" id="12">OBJECTIVE: Train enough units to defeat the pirates.  Train at least four hoplites and one centaur.</objective>
  <objective mission="04" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Protect Atlantis by killing Krakens and Pirates.</objective>
  <objective mission="04" id="2">OBJECTIVE: Build up and protect Atlantis by killing Krakens and Pirates.</objective>
  <objective mission="05" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Destroy the settlement at the center of the pirate base.</objective>
  <objective mission="05" id="2">OBJECTIVE: Corner and defeat Kamos.</objective>
  <objective mission="06" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Lead your men to the unclaimed settlement.</objective>
  <objective mission="06" id="2">OBJECTIVE: Claim the settlement and build an Archery Range and an Academy.</objective>
  <objective mission="06" id="3">OBJECTIVE: Fight through Troy's outer defenses and defeat the two guardians at the south gate.  OPTIONAL OBJECTIVE: Destroy the Trojan docks to receive reinforcements.</objective>
  <objective mission="06" id="4">OBJECTIVE: Fight through Troy's outer defenses and defeat the two guardians at the south gate.</objective>
  <objective mission="07" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Establish a camp and build up your forces to destroy the Trojan Gate.</objective>
  <objective mission="07" id="2">OBJECTIVE 1: Establish a camp and build up your forces to destroy the Trojan Gate.OPTIONAL OBJECTIVE: Destroy Troy's trade caravans to disrupt their economy and distract their military.</objective>
  <objective mission="08" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Save Ajax!  Destroy  the counter-attacking Trojan cavalry army.</objective>
  <objective mission="08" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Bring Arkantos, Odysseus and your army to Ajax's Town Center camp.</objective>
  <objective mission="08" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Strengthen your army, then destroy the revealed Trojan forward base in the north, outside of Troy.  Seige is unavailable: you may not build a Fortress.</objective>
  <objective mission="08" id="4">OBJECTIVE 3: Strengthen your army, then destroy the revealed Trojan forward base in the north, outside of Troy.   Seige is unavailable: you may not build a Fortress.  CAUTION:  Be alert to kill Trojan villagers coming to build near your resources or town.</objective>
  <objective mission="09" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Gather 500 wood to build the Trojan Horse.  Do not allow the build site to be discovered by scouts, they will bring armed patrols if they make it back to the city gates.</objective>
  <objective mission="09" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Build the Trojan Horse.  Do not allow the build site to be discovered by scouts, they will bring armed patrols if they make it back to the city gates.</objective>
  <objective mission="09" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Move the Trojan Horse to the flagged area to the East and avoid the gate patrols.</objective>
  <objective mission="09" id="4">OBJECTIVE 4: Ungarrison your Heroes and move them to the highlighted Gate of Troy.  Use them to destroy the gate.  Avoid detection if possible.</objective>
  <objective mission="09" id="5">OBJECTIVE 5: Defeat Troy by destroying all Fortresses within its walls.</objective>
  <objective mission="10" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Bring Arkantos and Ajax to the flagged area to rescue the hostages.  Your ships are too damaged to use.</objective>
  <objective mission="10" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Escape the prison: bring all of your units near the settlement to the west.</objective>
  <objective mission="10" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Attack the large boulder just east of the settlement to block pursuit.</objective>
  <objective mission="10" id="4">OBJECTIVE 4: Build up a military force to assault Shaba Ka's fortified acropolis, and destroy the fortress within it which holds Chiron.</objective>
  <objective mission="10" id="5">OBJECTIVE 4: Build up a military force to assault Shaba Ka's fortified acropolis, and destroy the fortress within it which holds Chiron.  OPTIONAL: Some damaged buildings in the town of Ioklos can be used.  Move any unit near a building to see whether it can be used (converted.)</objective>
  <objective mission="11" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Destroy the 2 fortresses guarding the mine entrance to the North.Hint: Co-ordinate your forces on both sides to progress through the canyons.</objective>
  <objective mission="12" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Defend the wooden access bridge -- your waves of reinforcements will need it to reach the giant siege ram.</objective>
  <objective mission="12" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Destroy the giant siege ram before it breaks down the great door.</objective>
  <objective mission="12" id="3">OBJECTIVE 2:  Destroy the giant siege ram before it breaks down the great door.  (OPTIONAL OBJECTIVE:) Block some of the enemy's feeder tunnels to slow his attack waves.  To block a tunnel, attack a large boulder at it's mouth, or destroy an enemy bridge.</objective>
  <objective mission="13" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Follow the Shades! They will help you safely navigate the dangers of the Underworld.</objective>
  <objective mission="13" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Bring the three Underworld Relics to the Wonder. Use the Shades to protect the Heroes and to explore.</objective>
  <objective mission="14" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Defend yourself from the armies coming from the canyons to the north, to buy time to unbury the Holy Relic near the fallen statues.  To unbury the Relic, task villagers on the sand mound near the fallen statues.  You are in the Classical Age and may not build a Town Center.</objective>
  <objective mission="15" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Escort the relic sword safely to the sleeping Guardian.</objective>
  <objective mission="15" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Destroy the nearby settlement to free the enslaved villagers.</objective>
  <objective mission="15" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3:  Use your heroes to lead the villagers (yellow) safely to their home settlement (yellow).</objective>
  <objective mission="15" id="4">OBJECTIVE 4: Carry the relic sword to the sleeping Guardian before Shaba Ka's main army returns.</objective>
  <objective mission="15" id="5">OBJECTIVE 5: Use the Guardian to destroy the 3 pyramids in Shaba Ka's fortress.</objective>
  <objective mission="16" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Gain control of the Osiris part and... ahhh, fergit it!  Just get David Leary to play this scenario for you!  He's the Mastah!  ; )</objective>
  <objective mission="16" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Gather resources and build an army to recover the Osiris Part Cart before the enemy can move it into their town. Move the Osiris Part Cart across the river and into the city to the Northwest.</objective>
  <objective mission="17" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Build up an army and use it to destroy the Abydos military complex citadel as a diversionary tactic.</objective>
  <objective mission="17" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Bring Amanra to the transport ship.</objective>
  <objective mission="17" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3:  Use the transport ship to transport Amanra to the flagged area, then break into the prison.  </objective>
  <objective mission="18" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Release the prisoners by destroying the gates and defend the prison area until your transports arrive from the Southwest.</objective>
  <objective mission="18" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Use the transports to move your troops to the flagged area near the yellow town to the Southwest.</objective>
  <objective mission="18" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Capture the Osiris Part and move it to the flag outside the city's South Gate.</objective>
  <objective mission="19" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Follow Kastor.</objective>
  <objective mission="19" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Garrison the relic into the temple.</objective>
  <objective mission="19" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Defeat the guardians around the shrine.  Trust Athena to assist you.</objective>
  <objective mission="19" id="4">OBJECTIVE 4: Destroy the large boulder to escape the underworld.</objective>
  <objective mission="19" id="5">OBJECTIVE 5: Transport Arkantos and Kastor to the flagged area.</objective>
  <objective mission="19" id="6">OBJECTIVE 6: Use your forces to destroy the Wonder.</objective>
  <objective mission="20" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Amanra must find villagers and enlist their help to build a settlement and establish a military base.</objective>
  <objective mission="20" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Bring Amanra to the Great Box on the island citadel, which holds a part of Osiris.  Build an invasion force and transport it to the island, to clear Amanra's way to the Great Box.</objective>
  <objective mission="21" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Seek help from the desert nomad camp to the east.</objective>
  <objective mission="21" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Send villagers to cut down the Tamarisk Tree and recover the head of Osiris.  OPTIONAL: Destroy the two tombs south of the river to stop mummy attacks.</objective>
  <objective mission="21" id="3">OBJECTIVE 2: Send villagers to cut down the Tamarisk Tree and recover the head of Osiris.</objective>
  <objective mission="22" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Capture the Black Sail Ships to the East by destroying the towers that guard them.</objective>
  <objective mission="22" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Use the Black Sail Ships to transport troops across the bay to the enemy base.  Find and defeat Kamos.</objective>
  <objective mission="22" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3:  Kamos has been found at the North side of the base.  Eliminate his troops and defeat him.</objective>
  <objective mission="23" id="1">OBJECTIVE: Build up and fight through Gargarensis's forces to the Osiris Pyramid.  Bring all 3 pieces of Osiris near the Great Box in front of the Pyramid.  You will not be able to gather resources, but you can build with your villagers.</objective>
  <objective mission="24" id="4">OBJECTIVE 1: A villager is going to slaughter the pigs! Save them!</objective>
  <objective mission="24" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Collect and protect 10 of the pigs. Villagers and worse prowl the island - beware!</objective>
  <objective mission="24" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Find a way through the gates and beyond the city to the Greater Temple where Zeus will return the pigs to human form. </objective>
  <objective mission="24" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Build up and defeat Circe by destroying the Fortress at the heart of the citadel.</objective>
  <objective mission="25" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Re-unite your forces and build a settlement to start your base. HINT: Seek shelter from the wolves during the dark winter storms by garrisonning your units inside buildings.</objective>
  <objective mission="25" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Build up your forces, then find and destroy the 3 Temples that are responsible for the monsters in the pass.HINT: Seek shelter from the wolves during the dark winter storms by garrisonning your units inside buildings.</objective>
  <objective mission="26" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Establish a base and build up.  Scout for entrances into the dwarfish mines.</objective>
  <objective mission="26" id="2">OBJECTIVE 1:  Establish a base and build up.  OBJECTIVE 2:  Capture the underground Dwarvish Forge.  (To capture the Forge, bring any of your heroes near it.)</objective>
  <objective mission="26" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Defend the Forge!  Defeat 3 Fire Giants for victory.</objective>
  <objective mission="27" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Move Arkantos along the path to the North side of the pass near the flag.  Find the hermit Skult, he may be able to help you.</objective>
  <objective mission="27" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Move Arkantos and Skult along the path to the North side of the pass near the flag.  Skult and Arkantos must survive.</objective>
  <objective mission="27" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Build seige weapons to break through the Boulder Wall.  Build up your defenses against more Giant attacks.  Skult and Arkantos must survive.</objective>
  <objective mission="27" id="4">OBJECTIVE 4: Break through the Boulder Wall and flee from the Giant army.  Move Skult and Arkantos to the flag at the North end of the pass.  Skult and Arkantos must survive.</objective>
  <objective mission="28" id="1">OBJECTIVE: The Norsemen are attacking - fight back!  Keep the banner bearer alive.  </objective>
  <objective mission="28" id="2">OBJECTIVE: Build a camp to replace units lost in the attack. Kill the clan leaders to stop the Norse attacks and gain the loyalty of their warriors.  Use the banner to lure enemies into ambush or away from their towns.</objective>
  <objective mission="28" id="3">OBJECTIVE: Kill the 3 clan leaders to stop the Norse attacks.  Use the banner to lure enemies into ambush or away from their towns.</objective>
  <objective mission="29" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: There are three clans in the Valley.  Find them and convince them to join together against Gargarensis.</objective>
  <objective mission="29" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Defeat the trolls in the mines to the north.  Blackhammer(GREEN) will join the heroes if the trolls are destroyed.</objective>
  <objective mission="29" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Take the tunnel to reach the next clan. (Head West through the pass for now)</objective>
  <objective mission="29" id="4">OBJECTIVE 4: Lothbrok's clan (MAGENTA) will join the heroes if their village is safe.  Build some walls and  towers around Lothbrok's village.</objective>
  <objective mission="29" id="5">OBJECTIVE 6: Cross the river to find Forkbeard's clan (YELLOW).</objective>
  <objective mission="29" id="6">OBJECTIVE 7: Forkbeard will join the heroes if his daughter is rescued.  She is held captive by Giants to the South.</objective>
  <objective mission="29" id="7">OBJECTIVE 5: The heroes must meet Lothbrok in the shrine circle.</objective>
  <objective mission="29" id="8">OBJECTIVE 8: Destroy the tower to free Forkbeard's daughter.</objective>
  <objective mission="30" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Build up a powerful army and destroy the gate to the Well of Mimir.</objective>
  <objective mission="30" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Defeat all of the myth units defending the Well!</objective>
  <objective mission="31" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Build up a base around the entrance to the Well of Mimir in snowy Midguard.  Build military units and send them through the Well to re-inforce Arkantos.Fight to the Tartarus gate and kill the enemy villagers that swing the Gate Ram before it swings 10 TIMES.REMINDER:  You cannot build buiildings or units in the Underworld.</objective>
  <objective mission="31" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Retreat across the Lava Bridge and protect the exit of the Well of Mimir from the enemy counter-attack for 10 minutes.  </objective>
  <objective mission="32" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Protect the dwarves until they cut the haft from the taproot.   Bring the head of Thor's hammer closer to the taproot, but do not let the enemy capture it. </objective>
  <objective mission="32" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Bring the two pieces of Thor's hammer together.  Do not let the enemy capture either piece.</objective>
  <objective mission="33" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Build a town center and erect defenses to protect it, including walls and the Stone Wall technology.</objective>
  <objective mission="33" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Survive for 20 minutes, until Odysseus and his army arrive.</objective>
  <objective mission="33" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3:  Kill Gargarensis.</objective>
  <objective mission="34" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Use Pegasus to find a spot to land your troops on Atlantis's shores.  Begin construction of a base by claiming a settlement.  </objective>
  <objective mission="34" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Build up a base and rescue 15 Atlantean Villagers from the Enemy.  Transport them across the sea to the Island Towers and garrison 5 villagers in each tower.  </objective>
  <objective mission="35" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1:  Build up a base and then construct a Wonder.  Zeus will reward you with a Titan.HINT: Capture the Plenty Vaults to gather resources faster.  Zeus will reward you with a METEOR GodPower for every Poseidon Temple you destroy.</objective>
  <objective mission="35" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2:  Zeus has given you a Titan. Use the Titan to destroy the animated Statue of Poseidon. HINT: Capture the Plenty Vaults to gather resources faster.  Zeus will reward you with a METEOR GodPower for every Poseidon Temple you destroy.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Gather 100 food, 100 gold, and 100 wood.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Bring additional villagers to pray at your Temple to gather 100 favor.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="3">
  </objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="4">OBJECTIVE 3: Train 3 Egyptian villagers from your Town Center.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="5">OBJECTIVE 4: Task your pharaoh onto your Town Center to bless it and increase its productivity.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="6">OBJECTIVE 5: Task your villagers to build 1 monument.  Unlike the Greeks, the Egyptians gather favor by building monuments.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="7">OBJECTIVE 6: The more monuments you have, the faster favor is generated.  Build additional monuments and generate 15 favor.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="8">OBJECTIVE 7: Select your flashing Priest, and move him near your flashing injured Chariot Archers to heal them.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="9">
  </objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="10">OBJECTIVE 8: Move you Ox Cart near your dwarves and task them to gather 200 gold.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="11">OBJECTIVE 9: Move you Ox Cart north to the forest and task your villagers to gather 200 wood.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="12">OBJECTIVE 10:  Use your Ulfsark warriors to build an armory.  Only Norse infantry units may build buildings.</objective>
  <objective mission="101" id="13">OBJECTIVE 11: Norse gather favor in battle.  Invade the enemy town and gather 30 favor!</objective>
  <objective mission="102" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: Build a Temple and advance to the Classical Age.</objective>
  <objective mission="102" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Build an Armory and advance to the Heroic Age.</objective>
  <objective mission="102" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: Build a Market and advance to the Olympic Age.</objective>
  <objective mission="102" id="4">OBJECTIVE 4: Destroy the enemy Town Center.  Your God Powers can help you win.</objective>
  <objective mission="103" id="1">OBJECTIVE 1: This is the Frost Giant.  Use the Mythological Units in each canyon to destroy the Red enemy troops.</objective>
  <objective mission="103" id="2">OBJECTIVE 2: Build a Temple and then train Myth units and villagers until you cannot train any more.</objective>
  <objective mission="103" id="3">OBJECTIVE 3: You are at your population cap. Build 3 more houses to gain more population room.</objective>
  <objective mission="103" id="4">OBJECTIVE 4: Build villagers and increase the size of your Army until you cannot build any more units.</objective>
  <objective mission="103" id="5">OBJECTIVE 5: Claim the unclaimed settlement by building a Town center on it to gain more population room.</objective>
  <objective mission="103" id="6">OBJECTIVE 6: Destroy the red enemy's Town Center and claim his settlement to win.</objective>
</objectivestext>